<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mongodb | tool monkey]]></title>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/categories/mongodb/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-22T13:10:37-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[erikerlandson@yahoo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pretty Good Random Sampling from Database Queries]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2012/05/16/pretty-good-random-sampling-from-database-queries/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-16T07:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2012/05/16/pretty-good-random-sampling-from-database-queries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Suppose you want to add random sampling to a database query, but your database does not support it.  One known technique is to add a field, say "rk", that contains a random key value in [0,1), index on that field, and add a clause to the query:  <code>("rk" &gt;= x  &amp;&amp;  "rk" &lt; x+p)</code>, where p is your desired random sampling probability and x is randomly chosen from [0,1-p).</p>

<p>This is not bad, but we can see it is not <em>truly</em> randomized, as the sliding window [x,x+p) over the "rk" random key field generates overlap in the samplings.  The larger the value of p, the more significant the overlapping effect will be.</p>

<p>Eliminating this effect absolutely (and maintaining query efficiency) is difficult without direct database support, however we can take steps to significantly reduce it.  Suppose we generated <em>two</em> independently randomized keys "rk0" and "rk1".  We could sample using a slightly more complex clause: <code>(("rk0" &gt;= x0  &amp;&amp; "rk0" &lt; x0+d) || ("rk1" &gt;= x1  &amp;&amp;  "rk1" &lt; x1+d))</code>, where x0 and x1 are randomly selected from [0,1-d).</p>

<p>What value do we use for d to maintain a random sampling factor of p?  As "rk0" and "rk1" are independent random variables, the effective sampling factor p is given by p = d + d - d<sup>2,</sup> where the d<sup>2</sup> accounts for query results present in both the "rk0" and "rk1" subqueries.  Applying the quadratic formula to solve for d gives us: d = 1-sqrt(1-p).</p>

<p>This approach should be useable with any database.  Here is example code I wrote for generating the random sampling portion of a mongodb query in pymongo:</p>

<pre><code>def random_sampling_query(p, rk0="rk0", rk1="rk1", pad = 0):
    d = (1.0 - sqrt(1.0-p)) * (1.0 + pad)
    if d &gt; 1.0: d = 1.0
    if d &lt; 0.0: d = 0.0
    s0 = random.random()*(1.0 - d)
    s1 = random.random()*(1.0 - d)
    return {"$or":[{rk0:{"$gte":s0, "$lt":s0+d}}, {rk1:{"$gte":s1, "$lt":s1+d}}]}
</code></pre>

<p>I included an optional 'pad' parameter to support a case where one might want a particular (integer) sample size s, and so set p = s/(db-table-size), and use padding to mitigate the probability of getting less than s records due to random sampling jitter.  In mongodb one could then append <code>limit(s)</code> to the query return, and get exactly s returns in most cases, with the correct padding.</p>

<p>Here is a pymongo example of using the <code>random_sampling_query()</code> above:</p>

<pre><code># get a query that does random sampling of 1% of the results:
query = random_sampling_query(0.01)
# other query clauses can be added if desired:
query[user] = "eje"
# issue the final query to get results with random sampling:
qres = data.find(query)
</code></pre>

<p>One could extend the logic above by using 3 independent random fields rk0,rk1,rk2 and applying the cubic formula, or four fields and the quartic formula, but I suspect that is passing the point of diminishing returns on storage cost, query cost and algebra.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
