<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: trigamma function | tool monkey]]></title>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/categories/trigamma-function/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-10T13:12:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[erikerlandson@yahoo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computing Derivatives of the Gamma Function]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/06/15/computing-derivatives-of-the-gamma-function/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-15T16:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/06/15/computing-derivatives-of-the-gamma-function</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I'll describe a simple algorithm to compute the kth derivatives of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_function">Gamma function</a>.</p>

<p>I'll start by showing a simple recursion relation for these derivatives, and then gives its derivation.  The kth derivative of Gamma(x) can be computed as follows:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/hvqtl52.png" alt="Equation 1" /></p>

<p>The recursive formula for the D<sub>k</sub> functions has an easy inductive proof:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/h79ued9.png" alt="Equation 2" /></p>

<p>Computing the next value D<sub>k</sub> requires knowledge of D<sub>k-1</sub> but also derivative D'<sub>k-1</sub>.  If we start expanding terms, we see the following:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/hhvonpa.png" alt="Equation 3" /></p>

<p>Continuing the process above it is not hard to see that we can continue expanding until we are left only with terms of <nobr>D<sub>1</sub><sup>(*)</sup>(x);</nobr> that is, various derivatives of <nobr>D<sub>1</sub>(x)</nobr>.  Furthermore, each layer of substitutions adds an order to the derivatives, so that we will eventually be left with terms involving the derivatives of <nobr>D<sub>1</sub>(x)</nobr> up to the (k-1)th derivative. Note that these will all be successive orders of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygamma_function">polygamma function</a>.</p>

<p>What we want, to do these computations systematically, is a formula for computing the nth derivative of a term <nobr>D<sub>k</sub>(x)</nobr>.  Examining the first few such derivatives suggests a pattern:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/jqwqpzy.png" alt="Equation 4" /></p>

<p>Generalizing from the above, we see that the formula for the nth derivative is:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/jamccnh.png" alt="Equation 5" /></p>

<p>We are now in a position to fill in the triangular table of values, culminating in the value of <nobr>D<sub>k</sub>(x):</nobr></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/jj9ph5l.png" alt="Equation 6" /></p>

<p>As previously mentioned, the basis row of values <nobr>D<sub>1</sub><sup>(*)</sup>(x)</nobr> are the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygamma_function">polygamma functions</a> where <nobr>D<sub>1</sub><sup>(n)</sup>(x) = polygamma<sup>(n)</sup>(x)</nobr>.  The first two polygammas, order 0 and 1, are simply the digamma and trigamma functions, respectively, and are available with most numeric libraries.  Computing the general polygamma is a project, and blog post, for another time, but the standard polynomial approximation for the digamma function can of course be differentiated...  Happy Computing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
