<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gamma distribution | tool monkey]]></title>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/categories/gamma-distribution/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-06T14:40:49-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[erikerlandson@yahoo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Approximating a PDF of Distances With a Gamma Distribution]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/07/09/approximating-a-pdf-of-distances-with-a-gamma-distribution/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-09T11:25:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/07/09/approximating-a-pdf-of-distances-with-a-gamma-distribution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2016/06/08/exploring-the-effects-of-dimensionality-on-a-pdf-of-distances/">previous post</a> I discussed some unintuitive aspects of the distribution of distances as spatial dimension changes.  To help explain this to myself I derived a formula for this distribution, assuming a unit multivariate Gaussian.  For distance (aka radius) r, and spatial dimension d, the PDF of distances is:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dist_dist/gwwv5a5.png" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>Recall that the form of this PDF is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generalized_gamma_distribution">generalized gamma distribution</a>, with scale parameter <nobr>a=sqrt(2),</nobr> shape parameter p=2, and free shape parameter (d) representing the dimensionality.</p>

<p>I was interested in fitting parameters to such a distribution, using some distance data from a clustering algorithm.  <a href="https://www.scipy.org/">SciPy</a> comes with a predefined method for fitting generalized gamma parameters, however I wished to implement something similar using <a href="http://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-math/">Apache Commons Math</a>, which does not have native support for fitting a generalized gamma PDF.  I even went so far as to start working out <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2016/06/15/computing-derivatives-of-the-gamma-function/">some of the math</a> needed to augment the Commons Math <a href="http://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-math/apidocs/org/apache/commons/math3/analysis/differentiation/package-summary.html">Automatic Differentiation libraries</a> with Gamma function differentiation needed to numerically fit my parameters.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, I have been fitting a <em>non generalized</em> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_distribution">gamma distribution</a> to the distance data, as a sort of rough cut, using a fast <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_distribution#Maximum_likelihood_estimation">non-iterative approximation</a> to the parameter optimization.  Consistent with my habit of asking the obvious question last, I tried plotting this gamma approximation against distance data, to see how well it compared against the PDF that I derived.</p>

<p>Surprisingly (at least to me), my approximation using the gamma distribution is a very effective fit for spatial dimensionalities <nobr> >= 2 </nobr>:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gamma_approx/approx_plot.png" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p>As the plot shows, only for the 1-dimension case is the gamma approximation substiantially deviating.  In fact, the fit appears to get better as dimensionality increases.  To address the 1D case, I can easily test the fit of a half-gaussian as a possible model.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
