<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: computing | tool monkey]]></title>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/categories/computing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-06T16:15:42-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[erikerlandson@yahoo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Random Forest Clustering of Machine Package Configurations in Apache Spark]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/05/05/random-forest-clustering-of-machine-package-configurations/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-05T15:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/05/05/random-forest-clustering-of-machine-package-configurations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><head><style type="text/css">
.gist {max-height:500px; overflow:auto}
</style></head></p>

<p>In this post I am going to describe some results I obtained for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cluster_analysis">clustering</a> machines by which <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RPM_Package_Manager">RPM packages</a> that were installed on them.  The clustering technique I used was <a href="https://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~breiman/RandomForests/cc_home.htm#unsup">Random Forest Clustering</a>.</p>

<p><a name="data"></a></p>

<h5>The Data</h5>

<p>The data I clustered consisted of 135 machines, each with a list of installed RPM packages.  The number of unique package names among all 135 machines was 4397.  Each machine was assigned a vector of Boolean values: a value of <code>1</code> indicates that the corresponding RPM was installed on that machine.  This means that the clustering data occupied a space of nearly 4400 dimensions.  I discuss the implications of this <a href="#payoff">later in the post</a>, and what it has to do with Random Forest Clustering in particular.</p>

<p>For ease of navigation and digestion, the remainder of this post is organized in sections:</p>

<p><a href="#clustering">Introduction to Random Forest Clustering</a> <br>
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;  (<a href="#payoff">The Pay-Off</a>) <br>
<a href="#code">Package Configuration Clustering Code</a> <br>
<a href="#results">Clustering Results</a> <br>
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;  (<a href="#outliers">Outliers</a>) <br></p>

<p><a name="clustering"></a></p>

<h5>Random Forests and Random Forest Clustering</h5>

<p>Full explainations of <a href="https://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~breiman/RandomForests/cc_home.htm">Random Forests</a> and <a href="https://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~breiman/RandomForests/cc_home.htm#unsup">Random Forest Clustering</a> could easily occupy blog posts of their own, but I will attempt to summarize them briefly here.  Random Forest learning models <em>per se</em> are well covered in the machine learning community, and available in most machine learning toolkits.  With that in mind, I will focus on their application to Random Forest Clustering, as it is less commonly used.</p>

<p>A Random Forest is an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ensemble_learning">ensemble learning model</a>, consisting of some number of individual <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_tree_learning">decision trees</a>, each trained on a random subset of the training data, and which choose from a random subset of candidate features when learning each internal decision node.</p>

<p>Random Forest Clustering begins by training a Random Forest to distinguish between the data to be clustered, and a corresponding <em>synthetic</em> data set created by sampling from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marginal_distribution">marginal</a> distributions of each <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feature_vector">feature</a>.  If the data has well defined clusters in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joint_probability_distribution">joint feature space</a> (a common scenario), then the model can identify these clusters as standing out from the more homogeneous distribution of synthetic data.  A simple example of what this looks like in 2 dimensional data is displayed in Figure 1, where the dark red dots are the data to be clustered, and the lighter pink dots represent synthetic data generated from the marginal distributions:</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/rfc_machines/demo1_both.png" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>Each interior decision node, in each tree of a Random Forest, typically divides the space of feature vectors in half: the half-space &lt;= some threshold, and the half-space > that threshold.  The result is that the model learned for our data can be visualized as rectilinear regions of space.  In this simple example, these regions can be plotted directly over the data, and show that the Random Forest did indeed learn the location of the data clusters against the background of synthetic data:</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/rfc_machines/demo1_rules.png" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p>Once this model has been trained, the actual data to be clustered are evaluated against this model.  Each data element navigates the interior decision nodes and eventually arrives at a leaf-node of each tree in the Random Forest ensemble, as illustrated in the following schematic:</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/rfc_machines/eval_leafs.png" alt="Figure 3" /></p>

<p>A key insight of Random Forest Clustering is that if two objects (or, their feature vectors) are similar, then they are likely to arrive at the same leaf nodes more often than not.  As the figure above suggests, it means we can cluster objects by their corresponding vectors of leaf nodes, <em>instead</em> of their raw feature vectors.</p>

<p>If we map the points in our toy example to leaf ids in this way, and then cluster the results, we obtain the following two clusters, which correspond well with the structure of the data:</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/rfc_machines/demo1_clust.png" alt="Figure 4" /></p>

<p>A note on clustering leaf ids.  A leaf id is just that -- an identifier -- and in that respect a vector of leaf ids has no <em>algebra</em>; it is not meaningful to take an average of such identifiers, any more than it would be meaningful to take the average of people's names.  Pragmatically, what this means is that the popular <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-means_clustering">k-means clustering algorithm</a> <em>cannot</em> be applied to this problem.</p>

<p>These vectors do, however, have <em>distance</em>: for any pair of vectors, add 1 for each corresponding pair of leaf ids that differ.  If two data elements arrived at all the same leafs in the Random Forest model, all their leaf ids are the same, and their distance is zero (with respect to the model, they are the same).  Therefore, we <em>can</em> apply <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-medoids">k-medoids clustering</a>.</p>

<p><a name="payoff"></a></p>

<h5>The Pay-Off</h5>

<p>What does this somewhat indirect method of clustering buy us?  Why <em>not</em> just cluster objects by their raw feature vectors?</p>

<p>The problem is that in many real-world cases (unlike in our toy example above), feature vectors computed for objects have <em>many dimensions</em> -- hundreds, thousands, perhaps millions -- instead of the two dimensions in this example.  Computing distances on such objects, necessary for clustering, is often expensive, and worse yet the quality of these distances is frequently poor due to the fact that most features in large spaces will be poorly correlated with <em>any</em> structure in the data.  This problem is so common, and so important, it has a name: the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curse_of_dimensionality">Curse of Dimensionality</a>.</p>

<p>Random Forest Clustering, which clusters on vectors of leaf-node ids from the trees in the model, side-steps the curse of dimensionality because the Random Forest training process, by learning where the data is against the background of the synthetic data, has already identified the features that are useful for identifying the structure of the data!   If any particular feature was poorly correlated with that struture, it has already been ignored by the model.  In other words, a Random Forest Clustering model is implicitly examining <strong> <em>exactly those features that are most useful for clustering</em> </strong>, thus providing a cure for the Curse of Dimensionality.</p>

<p>The <a href="#data">machine package configurations</a> whose clustering I describe for this post are a good example of high dimensional data that is vulnerable to the Curse of Dimensionality.  The dimensionality of the feature space is nearly 4400, making distances between vectors potentially expensive to evaluate.  Any individual feature contributes little to the distance, having to contend with over 4000 other features.  Installed packages are also noisy.  Many packages, such as kernels, are installed everywhere.  Others may be installed but not used, making them potentially irrelevant to grouping machines.  Furthermore, there are only 135 machines, and so there are far more features than data examples, making this an underdetermined data set.</p>

<p>All of these factors make the machine package configuration data a good test of the strenghts of Random Forest Clustering.</p>

<p><a name="code"></a></p>

<h5>Package Configuration Clustering Code</h5>

<p>The implementation of Random Forest Clustering I used for the results in this post is a library available from the <a href="http://silex.freevariable.com/">silex project</a>, a package of analytics libraries and utilities for <a href="http://spark.apache.org/">Apache Spark</a>.</p>

<p>In this section I will describe three code fragments that load the machine configuration data, perform a Random Forest clustering, and format some of the output.  This is the code I ran to obtain the <a href="#results">results</a> described in the final section of this post.</p>

<p>The first fragment of code illustrates the logistics of loading the feature vectors from file <code>train.txt</code> that represent the installed-package configurations for each machine. A corresponding "parallel" file <code>nodesclean.txt</code> contains corresponding machine names for each vector.  A third companion file <code>rpms.txt</code> contains names of each installed package.  These are used to instantiate a specialized Scala function (<code>InvertibleIndexFunction</code>) between feature indexes and human-readable feature names (in this case, names of RPM packages).  Finally, another specialized function (<code>Extractor</code>) for instantiating Spark feature vectors is created.</p>

<p>Note: <code>Extractor</code> and <code>InvertibleIndexFunction</code> are also component libraries of <a href="http://silex.freevariable.com/">silex</a></p>

<p>```scala
// Load installed-package feature vectors
val fields = spark.textFile(s"$dataDir/train.txt").map(_.split(" ").toVector)</p>

<p>// Pair feature vectors with machine names
val nodes = spark.textFile(s"$dataDir/nodesclean.txt").map { _.split(" ")(1) }
val ids = fields.paste(nodes)</p>

<p>// Load map from feature indexes to package names
val inp = spark.textFile(s"$dataDir/rpms.txt").map(<em>.split(" "))
  .map(r => (r(0).toInt, r(1)))
  .collect.toVector.sorted
val nf = InvertibleIndexFunction(inp.map(</em>._2))</p>

<p>// A feature extractor maps features into sequence of doubles
val m = fields.first.length - 1
val ext = Extractor(m, (v: Vector[String]) => v.map(_.toDouble).tail :FeatureSeq)
  .withNames(nf)
  .withCategoryInfo(IndexFunction.constant(2, m))
```</p>

<p>The next section of code is where the work of Random Forest Clustering happens.  A <code>RandomForestCluster</code> object is instantiated, and configured.  Here, the configuration is for 7 clusters, 250 synthetic points (about twice as many synthetic points as true data), and a Random Forest of 20 trees.  Training against the input data is a simple call to the <code>run</code> method.</p>

<p>The <code>predictWithDistanceBy</code> method is then applied to the data paired with machine names, to yield tuples of cluster-id, distance to cluster center, and the associated machine name.  These tuples are split by distance into data with a cluster, and data considered to be "outliers" (i.e. elements far from any cluster center).  Lastly, the <code>histFeatures</code> method is applied, to examine the Random Forest Model and identify any commonly-used features.</p>

<p>```scala
// Train a Random Forest Clustering Model
val rfcModel = RandomForestCluster(ext)
  .setClusterK(7)
  .setSyntheticSS(250)
  .setRfNumTrees(20)
  .setSeed(37)
  .run(fields)</p>

<p>// Evaluate to get tuples: (cluster, distance, machine-name)
val cid = ids.map(rfcModel.predictWithDistanceBy(_)(x => x))</p>

<p>// Split by closest distances into clusters and outliers<br/>
val (clusters, outliers) = cid.splitFilter { case (<em>, dist, </em>) => dist &lt;= 5 }</p>

<p>// Generate a histogram of features used in the RF model
val featureHist = rfcModel.randomForestModel.histFeatures(ext.names)
```</p>

<p>The final code fragment simply formats clusters and outliers into a tabular form, as displayed in the <a href="#results">next section</a> of this post.  Note that there is neither Spark nor silex code here; standard Scala methods are sufficient to post-process the clustering data:</p>

<p>```scala
// Format clusters for display
val clusterStr = clusters.map { case (j, d, n) => (j, (d, n)) }
  .groupByKey
  .collect
  .map { case (j, nodes) =></p>

<pre><code>nodes.toSeq.sorted.map { case (d, n) =&gt; s"$d  $n" }.mkString("\n")
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  .mkString("\n\n")</p>

<p>// Format outliers for display
val outlierStr = outliers.collect
  .map { case (_, d,n) => (d, n) }
  .toVector.sorted
  .map { case (d, n) => s"$d  $n" }
  .mkString("\n")
```</p>

<p><a name="results"></a></p>

<h5>Package Configuration Clustering Results</h5>

<p>The result of running the code in the <a href="#code">previous section</a> is seven clusters of machines.  In the following files, the first column represents distance from the cluster center, and the second is the actual machine's node name.  A cluster distance of 0.0 indicates that the machine was indistinguishable from cluster center, as far as the Random Forest model was concerned.   The larger the distance, the more different from the cluster's center a machine was, in terms of its installed RPM packages.</p>

<p>Was the clustering meaningful?  Examining the first two clusters below is promising; the machine names in these clusters are clearly similar, likely configured for some common task by the IT department.  The first cluster of machines appears to be web servers and corresponding backend services.  It would be unsurprising to find their RPM configurations were similar.</p>

<p>The second cluster is a series of executor machines of varying sizes, but presumably these would be configured similarly to one another.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=cluster_1"></script>




<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=cluster_2"></script>


<p>The second pair of clusters (3 &amp; 4) are small.  All of their names are similar (and furthermore, similar to some machines in other clusters), and so an IT administrator might wonder why they ended up in oddball small clusters.  Perhaps they have some spurious, non-standard packages installed that ought to be cleaned up.  Identifying these kinds of structure in a clustering is one common clustering application.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=cluster_3"></script>




<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=cluster_4"></script>


<p>Cluster 5 is a series of bugzilla web servers and corresponding back-end bugzilla data base services.  Although they were clustered together, we see that the web servers have a larger distance from the center, indicating a somewhat different configuration.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=cluster_5"></script>


<p>Cluster 6 represents a group of performance-related machines.  Not all of these machines occupy the same distance, even though most of their names are similar.  These are also the same series of machines as in clusters 3 &amp; 4.  Does this indicate spurious package installations, or some other legitimate configuration difference?  A question for the IT department...</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=cluster_6"></script>


<p>Cluster 7 is by far the largest.  It is primarily a combination of OpenStack machines and yet more perf machines.   This clustering was relatively stable -- it appeared across multiple independent clustering runs.  Because of its stability I would suggest to an IT administrator that the performance and OpenStack machines are sharing some configuration similarities, and the performance machines in other clusters suggest that there might be yet more configuration anomalies.  Perhaps these were OpenStack nodes that were re-purposed as performance machines?  Yet another question for IT...</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=cluster_7"></script>


<p><a name="outliers"></a></p>

<h5>Outliers</h5>

<p>This last grouping represents machines which were "far" from any of the previous cluster centers.  They may be interpreted as "outliers" - machines that don't fit any model category.  Of these the node <code>frodo</code> is clearly somebody's personal machine, likely with a customized or idiosyncratic package configuration.  Unsurprising that it is farthest of all machines from any cluster, with distance 9.0.   The <code>jenkins</code> machine is also somewhat unique among the nodes, and so perhaps not surprising that its registers as anomalous.  The remaining machines match node series from other clusters.   Their large distance is another indication of spurious configurations for IT to examine.</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=outliers"></script>


<p>I will conclude with another useful feature of Random Forest Models, which is that you can interrogate them for information such as which features were used most frequently.  Here is a histogram of model features (in this case, installed packages) that were used most frequently in the clustering model.  This particular histogram i sinteresting, as no feature was used more than twice.  The remaining features were all used exactly once.  This is a bit unusual for a Random Forest model.  Frequently some features are used commonly, with a longer tail.  This histogram is rather "flat," which may be a consequence of there being many more features (over 4000 installed packages) than there are data elements (135 machines).  This makes the problem somewhat under-determined.  To its credit, the model still achieves a meaningful clustering.</p>

<p>Lastly I'll note that full histogram length was 186; in other words, of the nearly 4400 installed packages, the Random Forest model used only 186 of them -- a tiny fraction!  A nice illustration of Random Forest Clustering performing in the face of <a href="#payoff">high dimensionality</a>!</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/184d202560c628c0383c5050d9f4be24.js?file=histogram"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computing Simplex Vertex Locations From Pairwise Object Distances]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/03/26/computing-simplex-vertex-locations-from-pairwise-vertex-distances/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-26T16:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/03/26/computing-simplex-vertex-locations-from-pairwise-vertex-distances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Suppose I have a collection of (N) objects, and distances d(j,k) between each pair of objects (j) and (k); that is, my objects are members of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metric_space">metric space</a>.  I have no knowledge about my objects, beyond these pair-wise distances.  These objects could be construed as vertices in an (N-1) dimensional <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simplex">simplex</a>.  However, since I have no spatial information about my objects, I first need a way to assign spatial locations to each object, in vector space R<sup>(N-1),</sup> with only my object distances to work with.</p>

<p>In this post I will derive an algorithm for assigning vertex locations in R<sup>(N-1)</sup> for each of N objects, using only pairwise object distances.</p>

<p>I will assume that N >= 2, since at least two object are required to define a pairwise distance.  The case N=2 is easy, as I can assign vertex 1 to the origin, and vertex 2 to the point d(1,2), to form a 1-simplex (i.e. a line segment) whose single edge is just the distance between the two objects.  I will also assume that my N objects are distinct; that is, each pair has a non-zero distance.</p>

<p>Next consider an arbitrary N, and suppose I have already added vertices 1 through k.  The next vertex (k+1) must obey the pairwise distance relations, as follows:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/jm56vxq.png" alt="figure 1" /></p>

<p>Adding the new vertex (k+1) involves adding another dimension (k) to the simplex.  I define this new kth coordinate x(k) to be zero for the existing k vertices, as annotated above; only the new vertex (k+1) will have a non-zero kth coordinate.  Expanding the quadratic terms on the left yields the following form:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/jtm7dpq.png" alt="figure 2" /></p>

<p>The squared terms for the coordinates of the new vertex (k+1) are inconvenient, however I can get rid of them by subtracting pairs of equations above.  For example, if I subtract equation 1 from the remaining k-1 equations (2 through k), these squared terms disappear, leaving me with the following system of k-1 equations, which we can see is linear in the 1st k-1 coordinates of the new vertex.  Therefore, I know I'll be able to solve for those coordinates.  I can solve for the remaining kth coordinate by plugging it into the first distance equation:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/haovm32.png" alt="figure 3" /></p>

<p>To clarify matters, the equations above can be re-written as the following matrix equation, solveable by any linear systems library:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/h6qdtms.png" alt="figure 4" /></p>

<p>This gives me a recusion relation for adding a new vertex (k+1), given that I have already added the first k vertices.  The basis case of adding the first two vertices was already described above.  And so I can iteratively add all my vertices one at a time by applying the recursion relation.</p>

<p>As a corollary, assume that I have constructed a simplex having k vertices, as shown above, and I would like to assign a spatial location to a new object, (y), given its k distances to each vertex.  The corresponding distance relations are given by:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/zdw9uv8.png" alt="figure 5" /></p>

<p>I can apply a derivation very similar to the one above, to obtain the following linear equation for the (k-1) coordinates of (y):</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/zvr5jre.png" alt="figure 6" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Efficient Multiplexing for Spark RDDs]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/02/08/efficient-multiplexing-for-spark-rdds/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-08T10:09:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/02/08/efficient-multiplexing-for-spark-rdds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I'm going to propose a new abstract operation on <a href="http://spark.apache.org/docs/latest/programming-guide.html#resilient-distributed-datasets-rdds">Spark RDDs</a> -- <strong>multiplexing</strong> -- that makes some categories of operations on RDDs both easier to program and in many cases much faster.</p>

<p>My main working example will be the operation of splitting a collection of data elements into N randomly-selected subsamples.  This operation is quite common in machine learning, for the purpose of dividing data into a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_set">training and testing set</a>, or the related task of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross-validation_(statistics">creating folds for cross-validation</a>).</p>

<p>Consider the current standard RDD method for accomplishing this task, <code>randomSplit()</code>.  This method takes a collection of N weights, and returns N output RDDs, each of which contains a randomly-sampled subset of the input, proportional to the corresponding weight.  The <code>randomSplit()</code> method generates the jth output by running a random number generator (RNG) for each input data element and accepting all elements which are in the corresponding jth (normalized) weight range.  As a diagram, the process looks like this at each RDD partition:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/mux/randomsplit.png" title="Figure 1" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>The observation I want to draw attention to is that to produce the N output RDDs, it has to run a random sampling over every element in the input <em>for each output</em>.  So if you are splitting into 10 outputs (e.g. for a 10-fold cross-validation), you are re-sampling your input 10 times, the only difference being that each output is created using a different acceptance range for the RNG output.</p>

<p>To see what this looks like in code, consider a simplified version of random splitting that just takes an integer <code>n</code> and always produces (n) equally-weighted outputs:</p>

<p>```scala
def splitSample<a href="rdd:%20RDD[T],%20n:%20Int,%20seed:%20Long%20=%2042">T :ClassTag</a>: Seq[RDD[T]] = {
  Vector.tabulate(n) { j =></p>

<pre><code>rdd.mapPartitions { data =&gt;
  scala.util.Random.setSeed(seed)
  data.filter { unused =&gt; scala.util.Random.nextInt(n) == j }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>(Note that for this method to operate correctly, the RNG seed must be set to the same value each time, or the data will not be correctly partitioned)</p>

<p>While this approach to random splitting works fine, resampling the same data N times is somewhat wasteful.  However, it is possible to re-organize the computation so that the input data is sampled only once.  The idea is to run the RNG once per data element, and save the element into a randomly-chosen collection.  To make this work in the RDD compute model, all N output collections reside in a single row of an <em>intermediate</em> RDD -- a "manifold" RDD.  Each output RDD then takes its data from the corresponding collection in the manifold RDD, as in this diagram:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/mux/multiplex.png" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p>If you abstract the diagram above into a generalized operation, you end up with methods that might like the following:</p>

<p>```scala
def muxPartitions<a href="n:%20Int,%20f:%20(Int,%20Iterator[T]">U :ClassTag</a> => Seq[U],
  persist: StorageLevel): Seq[RDD[U]] = {
  val mux = self.mapPartitionsWithIndex { case (id, itr) =></p>

<pre><code>Iterator.single(f(id, itr))
</code></pre>

<p>  }.persist(persist)
  Vector.tabulate(n) { j => mux.mapPartitions { itr => Iterator.single(itr.next()(j)) } }
}</p>

<p>def flatMuxPartitions<a href="n:%20Int,%20f:%20(Int,%20Iterator[T]">U :ClassTag</a> => Seq[TraversableOnce[U]],
  persist: StorageLevel): Seq[RDD[U]] = {
  val mux = self.mapPartitionsWithIndex { case (id, itr) =></p>

<pre><code>Iterator.single(f(id, itr))
</code></pre>

<p>  }.persist(persist)
  Vector.tabulate(n) { j => mux.mapPartitions { itr => itr.next()(j).toIterator } }
}
```</p>

<p>Here, the operation of sampling is generalized to any user-supplied function that maps RDD partition data into a sequence of objects that are computed in a single pass, and then multiplexed to the final user-visible outputs.  Note that these functions take a <code>StorageLevel</code> argument that can be used to control the caching level of the internal "manifold" RDD.  This typically defaults to <code>MEMORY_ONLY</code>, so that the computation can be saved and re-used for efficiency.</p>

<p>An efficient split-sampling method based on multiplexing, as described above, might be written using <code>flatMuxPartitions</code> as follows:</p>

<p>```scala
def splitSampleMux<a href="rdd:%20RDD[T],%20n:%20Int,%0A%20%20persist:%20StorageLevel%20=%20MEMORY_ONLY,%0A%20%20seed:%20Long%20=%2042">T :ClassTag</a>: Seq[RDD[T]] =
  rdd.flatMuxPartitions(n, (id: Int, data: Iterator[T]) => {</p>

<pre><code>scala.util.Random.setSeed(id.toLong * seed)
val samples = Vector.fill(n) { scala.collection.mutable.ArrayBuffer.empty[T] }
data.foreach { e =&gt; samples(scala.util.Random.nextInt(n)) += e }
samples
</code></pre>

<p>  }, persist)
```</p>

<p>To test whether multiplexed RDDs actually improve compute efficiency, I collected run-time data at various split values of <code>n</code> (from 1 to 10), for both the non-multiplexing logic (equivalent to the standard <code>randomSplit</code>) and the multiplexed version:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/mux/benchmark.png" title="Figure 3" alt="Figure 3" /></p>

<p>As the timing data above show, the computation required to run a non-multiplexed version grows linearly with <code>n</code>, just as predicted.  The multiplexed version, by computing the (n) outputs in a single pass, takes a nearly constant amount of time regardless of how many samples the input is split into.</p>

<p>There are other potential applications for multiplexed RDDs.  Consider the following tuple-based versions of multiplexing:</p>

<p>```scala
def muxPartitions<a href="f:%20(Int,%20Iterator[T]">U1 :ClassTag, U2 :ClassTag</a> => (U1, U2),
  persist: StorageLevel): (RDD[U1], RDD[U2]) = {
  val mux = self.mapPartitionsWithIndex { case (id, itr) =></p>

<pre><code>Iterator.single(f(id, itr))
</code></pre>

<p>  }.persist(persist)
  val mux1 = mux.mapPartitions(itr => Iterator.single(itr.next.<em>1))
  val mux2 = mux.mapPartitions(itr => Iterator.single(itr.next.</em>2))
  (mux1, mux2)
}</p>

<p>def flatMuxPartitions<a href="f:%20(Int,%20Iterator[T]">U1 :ClassTag, U2 :ClassTag</a> => (TraversableOnce[U1], TraversableOnce[U2]),
  persist: StorageLevel): (RDD[U1], RDD[U2]) = {
  val mux = self.mapPartitionsWithIndex { case (id, itr) =></p>

<pre><code>Iterator.single(f(id, itr))
</code></pre>

<p>  }.persist(persist)
  val mux1 = mux.mapPartitions(itr => itr.next.<em>1.toIterator)
  val mux2 = mux.mapPartitions(itr => itr.next.</em>2.toIterator)
  (mux1, mux2)
}
```</p>

<p>Suppose you wanted to run an input-validation filter on some data, sending the data that pass validation into one RDD, and data that failed into a second RDD, paired with information about the error that occurred.  Data validation is a potentially expensive operation.  With multiplexing, you can easily write the filter to operate in a single efficient pass to obtain both the valid stream and the stream of error-data:</p>

<p>```scala
def validate<a href="rdd:%20RDD[T],%20validator:%20T%20=>%20Boolean">T :ClassTag</a> = {
  rdd.flatMuxPartitions((id: Int, data: Iterator[T]) => {</p>

<pre><code>val valid = scala.collection.mutable.ArrayBuffer.empty[T]
val bad = scala.collection.mutable.ArrayBuffer.empty[(T, Exception)]
data.foreach { e =&gt;
  try {
    if (!validator(e)) throw new Exception("returned false")
    valid += e
  } catch {
    case err: Exception =&gt; bad += (e, err)
  }
}
(valid, bad)
</code></pre>

<p>  })
}
```</p>

<p>RDD multiplexing is currently a <a href="https://github.com/willb/silex/pull/50">PR against the silex project</a>.  The code I used to run the timing experiments above is <a href="https://github.com/erikerlandson/silex/blob/blog/muxrdd/src/main/scala/com/redhat/et/silex/sample/split.scala#L90">saved for posterity here</a>.</p>

<p>Happy multiplexing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 'prepare' operation considered harmful in Algebird aggregation]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/11/24/the-prepare-operation-considered-harmful-in-algebird/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-24T16:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/11/24/the-prepare-operation-considered-harmful-in-algebird</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to make an argument that the Algebird <a href="http://twitter.github.io/algebird/#com.twitter.algebird.Aggregator">Aggregator</a> design, in particular its use of the <code>prepare</code> operation in a map-reduce context, has substantial inefficiencies, compared to an equivalent formulation that is more directly suited to taking advantage of Scala's <a href="http://www.scala-lang.org/api/current/index.html#scala.collection.Seq">aggregate method on collections</a> method.</p>

<p>Consider the definition of aggregation in the Aggregator class:</p>

<p><code>scala
def apply(inputs: TraversableOnce[A]): C = present(reduce(inputs.map(prepare)))
</code></p>

<p>You can see that it is a standard map/reduce operation, where <code>reduce</code> is defined as a monoidal (or semigroup -- more on this later) operation. Under the hood, it boils down to an invocation of Scala's <code>reduceLeft</code> method.  The key thing to notice is that the role of <code>prepare</code> is to map a collection of data elements into the required monoids, which are then aggregated using that monoid's <code>plus</code> operation.  In other words, <code>prepare</code> converts data elements into "singleton" monoids each representing a data element.</p>

<p>Now, if the monoid in question is simple, say some numeric type, this conversion is free, or nearly so.  For example, the conversion of an integer into the "integer monoid" is a no-op.  However, there are other kinds of "non-trivial" monoids, for which the conversion of a data element into its corresponding monoid may be costly.  In this post, I will be using the monoid defined by Scala Set[Int], where the monoid <code>plus</code> operation is set union, and of course the <code>zero</code> element is the empty set.</p>

<p>Consider the process of defining an Algebird aggregator for the task of generating the set of unique elements in a data set.  The corresponding <code>prepare</code> operation is: <code>prepare(e: Int) = Set(e)</code>.  A monoid trait that encodes this idea might look like the following.  (the code I used in this post can be found <a href="https://gist.github.com/erikerlandson/d96dc553bc51e0eb5e4b">here</a>)</p>

<p>```scala
// an algebird-like monoid with the 'prepare' operation
trait PreparedMonoid[M, E] {
  val zero: M
  def plus(m1: M, m2: M): M
  def prepare(e: E): M
}</p>

<p>// a PreparedMonoid for a set of integers.  monoid operator is set union.
object intSetPrepared extends PreparedMonoid[Set[Int], Int] {
  val zero = Set.empty[Int]
  def plus(m1: Set[Int], m2: Set[Int]) = m1 ++ m2
  def prepare(e: Int) = Set(e)
}</p>

<p>implicit class SeqWithMapReduce<a href="seq:%20Seq[E]">E</a> {
  // algebird map/reduce Aggregator model
  def mrPrepared<a href="mon:%20PreparedMonoid[M,%20E]">M</a>: M = {</p>

<pre><code>seq.map(mon.prepare).reduceLeft(mon.plus)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>If we unpack the above code, as applied to <code>intSetPrepared</code>, we are instantiating a new Set object, containing a single value, for every single input data element.</p>

<p>But there is a potentially better model of aggregation, exemplified by the Scala <code>aggregate</code> method.  This method does not use a <code>prepare</code> operation.  It uses a zero value and a monoidal operator, which the Scala docs refer to as <code>combop</code>, but it also uses an "update" operation, that defines how to update the monoid object, directly, with a single element, referred to as <code>seqop</code> in Scala's documentation.  This idea can also be encoded as a flavor of monoid, enhanced with an <code>update</code> method:</p>

<p>```scala
// an algebird-like monoid with 'update' operation
trait UpdatedMonoid[M, E] {
  val zero: M
  def plus(m1: M, m2: M): M
  def update(m: M, e: E): M
}</p>

<p>// an equivalent UpdatedMonoid for a set of integers
object intSetUpdated extends UpdatedMonoid[Set[Int], Int] {
  val zero = Set.empty[Int]
  def plus(m1: Set[Int], m2: Set[Int]) = m1 ++ m2
  def update(m: Set[Int], e: Int) = m + e
}</p>

<p>implicit class SeqWithMapReduceUpdated<a href="seq:%20Seq[E]">E</a> {
  // map/reduce logic, taking advantage of scala 'aggregate'
  def mrUpdatedAggregate<a href="mon:%20UpdatedMonoid[M,%20E]">M</a>: M = {</p>

<pre><code>seq.aggregate(mon.zero)(mon.update, mon.plus)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>This arrangement promises more efficiency when aggregating w.r.t. nontrivial monoids, by avoiding the construction of "singleton" monoids for each data element.  The following demo confirms that for the Set-based monoid, it is over 10 times faster:</p>

<p>```scala
scala> :load /home/eje/scala/prepare.scala
Loading /home/eje/scala/prepare.scala...
defined module prepare</p>

<p>scala> import prepare.<em>
import prepare.</em></p>

<p>scala> val data = Vector.fill(1000000) { scala.util.Random.nextInt(10) }
data: scala.collection.immutable.Vector[Int] = Vector(7, 9, 4, 2, 7,...</p>

<p>// Verify that output is the same for both implementations:
scala> data.mrPrepared(intSetPrepared)
res0: Set[Int] = Set(0, 5, 1, 6, 9, 2, 7, 3, 8, 4)</p>

<p>// results are the same
scala> data.mrUpdatedAggregate(intSetUpdated)
res1: Set[Int] = Set(0, 5, 1, 6, 9, 2, 7, 3, 8, 4)</p>

<p>// Compare timings of prepare-based versus update-based aggregation
// (benchmark values are returned in seconds)
scala> benchmark(10) { data.mrPrepared(intSetPrepared) }
res2: Double = 0.2957673056</p>

<p>// update-based aggregation is 10 times faster
scala> benchmark(10) { data.mrUpdatedAggregate(intSetUpdated) }
res3: Double = 0.027041249300000004
```</p>

<p>It is also possible to apply Scala's <code>aggregate</code> to a monoid enhanced with <code>prepare</code>:</p>

<p>```scala
implicit class SeqWithMapReducePrepared<a href="seq:%20Seq[E]">E</a> {
  // using 'aggregate' with prepared op
  def mrPreparedAggregate<a href="mon:%20PreparedMonoid[M,%20E]">M</a>: M = {</p>

<pre><code>seq.aggregate(mon.zero)((m, e) =&gt; mon.plus(m, mon.prepare(e)), mon.plus)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>Although this turns out to be measurably faster than the literal map-reduce implementation, it is still not nearly as fast as the variation using <code>update</code>:</p>

<p><code>scala
scala&gt; benchmark(10) { data.mrPreparedAggregate(intSetPrepared) }
res2: Double = 0.1754636707
</code></p>

<p>Readers familiar with Algebird may be wondering about my use of monoids above, when the <code>Aggregator</code> interface is actually based on semigroups.  This is important, since building on Scala's <code>aggregate</code> function requires a zero element that semigroups do not have.  Although I believe it might be worth considering changing <code>Aggregator</code> to use monoids, another sensible option is to change the internal logic for the subclass <code>AggregatorMonoid</code>, which does require a monoid, or possibly just define a new <code>AggregatorMonoidUpdated</code> subclass.</p>

<p>A final note on compatability: note that any monoid enhanced with <code>prepare</code> can be converted into an equivalent monoid enhanced with <code>update</code>, as demonstrated by this factory function:</p>

<p>```scala
object UpdatedMonoid {
  // create an UpdatedMonoid from a PreparedMonoid
  def apply<a href="mon:%20PreparedMonoid[M,%20E]">M, E</a> = new UpdatedMonoid[M, E] {</p>

<pre><code>val zero = mon.zero
def plus(m1: M, m2: M) = mon.plus(m1, m2)
def update(m: M, e: E) = mon.plus(m, mon.prepare(e))
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Very Fast Reservoir Sampling]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/11/20/very-fast-reservoir-sampling/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-20T11:27:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/11/20/very-fast-reservoir-sampling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I will demonstrate how to do reservoir sampling orders of magnitude faster than the traditional "naive" reservoir sampling algorithm, using a fast high-fidelity approximation to the reservoir sampling-gap distribution.</p>

<blockquote><p>The code I used to collect the data for this post can be viewed <a href="https://github.com/erikerlandson/silex/blob/blog/reservoir/src/main/scala/com/redhat/et/silex/sample/reservoir/reservoir.scala">here</a>.  I generated the plots using the <a href="https://github.com/quantifind/wisp">quantifind WISP</a> project.</p>

<p>Update (April 4, 2016): my colleague <a href="http://rnowling.github.io/">RJ Nowling</a> ran across a <a href="http://www.ittc.ku.edu/~jsv/Papers/Vit87.RandomSampling.pdf">paper by J.S. Vitter</a> that shows Vitter developed the trick of accelerating sampling with a sampling-gap distribution in 1987 -- I re-invented Vitter's wheel 30 years after the fact!  I'm surprised it never caught on, as it is not much harder to implement than the naive version.</p></blockquote>

<p>In a <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/faster-random-samples-with-gap-sampling/">previous post</a>, I showed that random Bernoulli and Poisson sampling could be made much faster by modeling the <em>sampling gap distribution</em> for the corresponding sampling distributions.  More recently, I also began exploring whether <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reservoir_sampling">reservoir sampling</a> might also be optimized using the gap sampling technique, by deriving the <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2015/08/17/the-reservoir-sampling-gap-distribution/">reservoir sampling gap distribution</a>.  For a sampling reservoir of size (R), starting at data element (j), the probability distribution of the sampling gap is:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure6.png" title="Figure 1" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>Modeling a sampling gap distribution is a powerful tool for optimizing a sampling algorithm, but it presupposes that you can actually draw values from that distribution substantially faster than just applying a random process to drawing each data element.  I was unable to come up with a "direct" algorithm for drawing samples from P(k) above (I suspect none exists), however I also know the CDF F(k), so it <em>is</em> possible to apply <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverse_transform_sampling">inversion sampling</a>, which runs in logarithmic time w.r.t the desired accuracy.  Although its logarithmic cost effectively guarantees that it will be a net efficiency win for sufficiently large (j), it still involves a substantial number of computations to yield its samples, and it seems unlikely to be competitive with straight "naive" reservoir sampling over many real-world data sizes, where (j) may never grow very large.</p>

<p>Well, if exact computations are too expensive, we can always look for a fast approximation.  Consider the original "first principles" formula for the sampling gap P(k):</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/figure2.png" title="Figure 2" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p>As the figure above alludes to, if (j) is relatively large compared to (k), then values (j+1),(j+2)...(j+k) are all going to be effectively "close" to (j), and so we can replace them all with (j) as an approximation.  Note that the resulting approximation is just the PMF of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geometric_distribution">geometric distribution</a>, with probability of success p=(R/j), and we already saw how to efficiently draw values from a geometric distribution from our experience with Bernoulli sampling.</p>

<p>Do we have any reason to hope that this approximation will be useful?  For reasons that are similar to those for Bernoulli gap sampling, it will only be efficient to employ gap sampling when the probability (R/j) becomes small enough.  From our experiences with Bernoulli sampling that is <em>at least</em> j>=2R.  So, we have some assurance that (j) itself will be never be <em>very</em> small.  What about (k)?  Note that a geometric distribution "favors" smaller values of (k) -- that is, small values of (k) have the highest probabilities.  In fact, the smaller that (j) is, the larger the probability (R/j) is, and so the more likely that (k) values that are small relative to (j) will be the frequent ones.  It is also promising that the true distribution for P(k) <em>also</em> favors smaller values of (k) (in fact it favors them even a bit more strongly than the approximation).</p>

<p>Although it is encouraging, it is also clear that my argument above is limited to heuristic hand-waving.  What does this approximation really <em>look</em> like, compared to the true distribution?  Fortunately, it is easy to plot both distributions numerically, since we now know the formulas for both:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/CDFs_R=10.png" title="Figure 3" alt="Figure 3" /></p>

<p>The plot above shows that, in fact, the geometric approximation is a <em>surprisingly good</em> approximation to the true distribution!  Furthermore, the approximation remains good as both (j) and (k) grow larger.</p>

<p>Our numeric eye-balling looks quite promising.  Is there an effective way to <em>measure</em> how good this approximation is?  One useful measure is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kolmogorov%E2%80%93Smirnov_test">Kolmogorov-Smirnov D statistic</a>, which is just the maximum absolute error between two cumulative distributions.  Here is a plot of the D statistic for reservoir size R=10, as (j) varies across several magnitudes:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/R=10.png" title="Figure 4" alt="Figure 4" /></p>

<p>This plot is also good news: we can see that deviation, as measured by D, remains bounded at a small value (less than 0.0262).  As this is for the specific value R=10, we also want to know how things change as reservoir size changes:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/R=all.png" title="Figure 5" alt="Figure 5" /></p>

<p>The news is still good!  As reservoir size grows, the approximation only gets better: the D values get smaller as R increases, and remain asymptotically bounded as (j) increases.</p>

<p>Now we have some numeric assurance that the geometric approximation is a good one, and stays good as reservoir size grows and sampling runs get longer.  However, we should also verify that an actual implementation of the approximation works as expected.</p>

<p>Here is pseudocode for an implementation of reservoir sampling using the fast geometric approximation:</p>

<pre><code>// data is array to sample from
// R is the reservoir size
function reservoirFast(data: Array, R: Int) {
  n = data.length
  // Initialize reservoir with first R elements of data:
  res = data[0 until R]
  // Until this threshold, use traditional sampling.  This value may
  // depend on performance characteristics of random number generation and/or
  // numeric libraries:
  t = 4 * R
  j = 1 + R
  while (j &lt; n  &amp;&amp;  j &lt;= t) {
    k = randomInt(j) // random integer &gt;= 0 and &lt; j
    if (k &lt; R) res[k] = data[j]
    j = j + 1
  }
  // Once gaps become significant, it pays to do gap sampling
  while (j &lt; n) {
    // draw gap size (g) from geometric distribution with probability p = R/j
    p = R / j
    u = randomFloat() // random float &gt; 0 and &lt;= 1
    g = floor(log(u) / log(1-p))
    j = j + g
    if (j &lt; n) {
      k = randomInt(R)
      res[k] = data[j]
    }
    j = j + 1
  }
  // return the reservoir
  return res
}
</code></pre>

<p>Following is a plot that shows two-sample D statistics, comparing the distribution in sample gaps between runs of the exact "naive" reservoir sampling with the fast geometric approximation:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/D_naive_vs_fast.png" title="Figure 6" alt="Figure 6" /></p>

<p>As expected, the measured difference in sampling characteristics between naive and fast approximation are small, confirming the numeric predictions.</p>

<p>Since the point of this exercise was to achieve faster random sampling, it remains to measure what kind of speed improvements the fast approximation provides.  As a point of reference, here is a plot of run times for reservoir sampling over 10<sup>8</sup> integers:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/naive_sample_time_vs_R.png" title="Figure 7" alt="Figure 7" /></p>

<p>As expected, sample time remains constant at around 1.5 seconds, regardless of reservoir size, since the naive algorithm always samples from its RNG per each sample.</p>

<p>Compare this to the corresponding plot for the fast geometric approximation:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/gap_sample_times_vs_R.png" title="Figure 8" alt="Figure 8" /></p>

<p>Firstly, we see that the sampling times are <em>much faster</em>, as originally anticipated in my <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2015/08/17/the-reservoir-sampling-gap-distribution/">previous post</a> -- in the neighborhood of 3 orders of magnitude faster.  Secondly, we see that the sampling times do increase as a linear function of reservoir size.  Based on our experience with Bernoulli gap sampling, this is expected; the sampling probabilities are given by (R/j), and therefore the amount of sampling is proportional to R.</p>

<p>Another property anticipated in my previous post was that the efficiency of gap sampling should continue to increase as the amount of data sampled grows; the sampling probability being (R/j), the probability of sampling decreases as j gets larger, and so the corresponding gap sizes grow.  The following plot verifies this property, holding reservoir size R constant, and increasing the data size:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/gap_sampling_efficiency.png" title="Figure 9" alt="Figure 9" /></p>

<p>The sampling time (per million elements) decreases as the sample size grows, as predicted by the formula.</p>

<p>In conclusion, I have demonstrated that a geometric distribution can be used as a high quality approximation to the true sampling gap distribution for reservoir sampling, which allows reservoir sampling to be performed much faster than the naive algorithm while still retaining sampling quality.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
