<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: break | tool monkey]]></title>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/categories/break/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-27T15:02:59-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[erikerlandson@yahoo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Monadic 'break' and 'continue' for Scala Sequence Comprehensions]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/01/24/monadic-break-and-continue-for-scala-sequence-comprehensions/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-24T11:54:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/01/24/monadic-break-and-continue-for-scala-sequence-comprehensions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Author's note: I've since received some excellent feedback from the Scala community, which I included in some <a href="#notes">end notes</a>.</p>

<p>Author's note the 2nd: I later realized I could apply an implicit conversion and mediator class to preserve the traditional ordering: the code has been updated with that approach.</p>

<p>Author's note the 3rd: This concept has been submitted to the Scala project as JIRA <a href="https://issues.scala-lang.org/browse/SI-9120">SI-9120</a> (PR <a href="https://github.com/scala/scala/pull/4275">#4275</a>)</p>

<p>Scala <a href="http://docs.scala-lang.org/tutorials/tour/sequence-comprehensions.html">sequence comprehensions</a> are an excellent functional programming idiom for looping in Scala.  However, sequence comprehensions encompass much more than just looping -- they represent a powerful syntax for manipulating <em>all</em> monadic structures<a href="#ref1">[1]</a>.</p>

<p>The <code>break</code> and <code>continue</code> looping constructs are a popular framework for cleanly representing multiple loop halting and continuation conditions at differing stages in the execution flow.  Although there is no native support for <code>break</code> or <code>continue</code> in Scala control constructs, it is possible to implement them in a clean and idiomatic way for sequence comprehensions.</p>

<p>In this post I will describe a lightweight and easy-to-use implementation of <code>break</code> and <code>continue</code> for use in Scala sequence comprehensions (aka <code>for</code> statements).  The entire implementation is as follows:</p>

<pre><code>object BreakableGenerators {
  import scala.language.implicitConversions

  type Generator[+A] = Iterator[A]
  type BreakableGenerator[+A] = BreakableIterator[A]

  // Generates a new breakable generator from any traversable object.
  def breakable[A](t1: TraversableOnce[A]): Generator[BreakableGenerator[A]] =
    List(new BreakableIterator(t1.toIterator)).iterator

  // Mediates boolean expression with 'break' and 'continue' invocations
  case class BreakableGuardCondition(cond: Boolean) {
    // Break the looping over one or more breakable generators, if 'cond' 
    // evaluates to true.
    def break(b: BreakableGenerator[_], bRest: BreakableGenerator[_]*): Boolean = {
      if (cond) {
        b.break
        for (x &lt;- bRest) { x.break }
      }
      !cond
    }

    // Continue to next iteration of enclosing generator if 'cond' 
    // evaluates to true.
    def continue: Boolean = !cond
  }

  // implicit conversion of boolean values to breakable guard condition mediary
  implicit def toBreakableGuardCondition(cond: Boolean) =
    BreakableGuardCondition(cond)

  // An iterator that can be halted via its 'break' method.  Not invoked directly
  class BreakableIterator[+A](itr: Iterator[A]) extends Iterator[A] {
    private var broken = false
    private[BreakableGenerators] def break { broken = true }

    def hasNext = !broken &amp;&amp; itr.hasNext
    def next = itr.next
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The approach is based on a simple subclass of <code>Iterator</code> -- <code>BreakableIterator</code> -- that can be halted by 'breaking' it.  The function <code>breakable(&lt;traversable-object&gt;)</code> returns an Iterator over a single <code>BreakableIterator</code> object.  Iterators are monad-like structures in that they implement <code>map</code> and <code>flatMap</code>, and so its output can be used with <code>&lt;-</code> at the start of a <code>for</code> construct in the usual way.  Note that this means the result of the <code>for</code> statement will also be an Iterator.</p>

<p>Whenever the boolean expression for an <code>if</code> guard is followed by either <code>break</code> or <code>continue</code>, it is implicitly converted to a "breakable guard condition" that supports those methods.  The function <code>break</code> accepts one or more instances of <code>BreakableIterator</code>.  If it evaluates to <code>true</code>, the loops embodied by the given iterators are immediately halted via the associated <code>if</code> guard, and the iterators are halted via their <code>break</code> method.  The <code>continue</code> function is mostly syntactic sugar for a standard <code>if</code> guard, simply with the condition inverted.</p>

<p>Here is a simple example of <code>break</code> and <code>continue</code> in use:</p>

<pre><code>object Main {
  import BreakableGenerators._

  def main(args: Array[String]) {

    val r = for (
      // generate a breakable sequence from some sequential input
      loop &lt;- breakable(1 to 1000);
      // iterate over the breakable sequence
      j &lt;- loop;
      // print out at each iteration
      _ = { println(s"iteration j= $j") };
      // continue to next iteration when 'j' is even
      if { j % 2 == 0 } continue;
      // break out of the loop when 'j' exceeds 5
      if { j &gt; 5 } break(loop)
    ) yield {
      j
    }
    println(s"result= ${r.toList}")
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>We can see from the resulting output that <code>break</code> and <code>continue</code> function in the usual way.  The <code>continue</code> clause ignores all subsequent code when <code>j</code> is even.  The <code>break</code> clause halts the loop when it sees its first value > 5, which is 7.  Only odd values &lt;= 5 are output from the <code>yield</code> statement:</p>

<pre><code>$ scalac -d /home/eje/class monadic_break.scala
$ scala -classpath /home/eje/class Main
iteration j= 1
iteration j= 2
iteration j= 3
iteration j= 4
iteration j= 5
iteration j= 6
iteration j= 7
result= List(1, 3, 5)
</code></pre>

<p>Breakable iterators can be nested in the way one would expect.  The following example shows an inner breakable loop nested inside an outer one:</p>

<pre><code>object Main {
  import BreakableGenerators._

  def main(args: Array[String]) {
    val r = for (
      outer &lt;- breakable(1 to 7);
      j &lt;- outer;
      _ = { println(s"outer  j= $j") };
      if { j % 2 == 0 } continue;
      inner &lt;- breakable(List("a", "b", "c", "d", "e"));
      k &lt;- inner;
      _ = { println(s"    inner  j= $j  k= $k") };
      if { k == "d" } break(inner);
      if { j == 5  &amp;&amp;  k == "c" } break(inner, outer)
    ) yield {
      (j, k)
    }
    println(s"result= ${r.toList}")
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The output demonstrates that the inner loop breaks whenever <code>k=="d"</code>, and so <code>"e"</code> is never present in the <code>yield</code> result.  When <code>j==5</code> and <code>k=="c"</code>, both the inner and outer loops are broken, and so we see that there is no <code>(5,"c")</code> pair in the result, nor does the outer loop ever iterate over 6 or 7:</p>

<pre><code>$ scalac -d /home/eje/class monadic_break.scala
$ scala -classpath /home/eje/class Main
outer  j= 1
    inner  j= 1  k= a
    inner  j= 1  k= b
    inner  j= 1  k= c
    inner  j= 1  k= d
outer  j= 2
outer  j= 3
    inner  j= 3  k= a
    inner  j= 3  k= b
    inner  j= 3  k= c
    inner  j= 3  k= d
outer  j= 4
outer  j= 5
    inner  j= 5  k= a
    inner  j= 5  k= b
    inner  j= 5  k= c
result= List((1,a), (1,b), (1,c), (3,a), (3,b), (3,c), (5,a), (5,b))
</code></pre>

<p>Using <code>break</code> and <code>continue</code> with <code>BreakableIterator</code> for sequence comprehensions is that easy.  Enjoy!</p>

<p><a name="notesname" id="notes"></a></p>

<h5>Notes</h5>

<p>The helpful community on freenode #scala made some excellent observations:</p>

<p>1: Iterators in Scala are not strictly monadic -- it would be more accurate to say they're "things with a flatMap and map method, also they can use filter or withFilter sometimes."  However, I personally still prefer to think of them as "monadic in spirit if not law."</p>

<p>2: The <code>break</code> function, as described in this post, is not truly functional in the sense of referential transparency, as the invocation <code>if break(loop) { condition }</code> involves a side-effect on the variable <code>loop</code>.  I would say that it does maintain "scoped functionality."  That is, the break in non-referential transparency is scoped by the variables in question.  The <code>for</code> statement containing them is referentially transparent with respect to its inputs (provided no other code is breaking referential transparency, of course).</p>

<h5>References</h5>

<p><a name="ref1name" id="ref1">[1] </a><em><a href="http://www.manning.com/bjarnason/">Functional Programming in Scala</a></em>, Paul Chiusano and Runar Bjarnason, (section 6.6)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
