<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: math | tool monkey]]></title>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/categories/math/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-05-29T06:31:05-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[erikerlandson@yahoo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computing Smooth Max and its Gradients Without Over- and Underflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2018/05/28/computing-smooth-max-and-its-gradients-without-over-and-underflow/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-28T08:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2018/05/28/computing-smooth-max-and-its-gradients-without-over-and-underflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2018/05/27/the-gradient-and-hessian-of-the-smooth-max-over-functions/">previous post</a> I derived the gradient and Hessian for the smooth max function.
The <a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/">Notorious JDC</a> wrote a helpful companion post that describes <a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2010/01/20/how-to-compute-the-soft-maximum/">computational issues</a> of overflow and underflow with smooth max;
values of f<sub>k</sub> don't have to grow very large (or small) before floating point limitations start to force their exponentials to +inf or zero.
In JDC's post he discusses this topic in terms of a two-valued smooth max.
However it isn't hard to generalize the idea to a collection of f<sub>k</sub>.
Start by taking the maximum value over our collection of functions, which I'll define as (z):</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/smoothmax/eq1b.png" alt="eq1" /></p>

<p>As JDC described in his post, this alternative expression for smooth max (m) is computationally stable.
Individual exponential terms may underflow to zero, but they are the ones which are dominated by the other terms, and so approximating them by zero is numerically accurate.
In the limit where one value dominates all others, it will be exactly the value given by (z).</p>

<p>It turns out that we can play a similar trick with computing the gradient:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/smoothmax/eq2b.png" alt="eq2" /></p>

<p>Without showing the derivation, we can apply exactly the same manipulation to the terms of the Hessian:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/smoothmax/eq3b.png" alt="eq3" /></p>

<p>And so we now have a computationally stable form of the equations for smooth max, its gradient and its Hessian. Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Gradient and Hessian of the Smooth Max Over Functions]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2018/05/27/the-gradient-and-hessian-of-the-smooth-max-over-functions/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-27T09:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2018/05/27/the-gradient-and-hessian-of-the-smooth-max-over-functions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Suppose you have a set of functions over a vector space, and you are interested in taking the smooth-maximum over those functions.
For example, maybe you are doing gradient descent, or convex optimization, etc, and you need a variant on "maximum" that has a defined gradient.
The smooth maximum function has both a defined gradient and Hessian, and in this post I derive them.</p>

<p>I am using the <a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2010/01/13/soft-maximum/">logarithm-based</a> definition of smooth-max, shown here:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/smoothmax/eq1.png" alt="eq1" /></p>

<p>I will use the second variation above, ignoring function arguments, with the hope of increasing clarity.
Applying the chain rule gives the ith partial gradient of smooth-max:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/smoothmax/eq2.png" alt="eq2" /></p>

<p>Now that we have an ith partial gradient, we can take the jth partial gradient of <em>that</em> to obtain the (i,j)th element of a Hessian:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/smoothmax/eq3.png" alt="eq3" /></p>

<p>This last re-grouping of terms allows us to see that we can express the full gradient and Hessian in the following more compact way:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/smoothmax/eq4.png" alt="eq4" /></p>

<p>With a gradient and Hessian, we now have the tools we need to use smooth-max in algorithms such as gradient descent and convex optimization. Happy computing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Approximating a PDF of Distances With a Gamma Distribution]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/07/09/approximating-a-pdf-of-distances-with-a-gamma-distribution/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-09T11:25:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/07/09/approximating-a-pdf-of-distances-with-a-gamma-distribution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2016/06/08/exploring-the-effects-of-dimensionality-on-a-pdf-of-distances/">previous post</a> I discussed some unintuitive aspects of the distribution of distances as spatial dimension changes.  To help explain this to myself I derived a formula for this distribution, assuming a unit multivariate Gaussian.  For distance (aka radius) r, and spatial dimension d, the PDF of distances is:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dist_dist/gwwv5a5.png" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>Recall that the form of this PDF is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generalized_gamma_distribution">generalized gamma distribution</a>, with scale parameter <nobr>a=sqrt(2),</nobr> shape parameter p=2, and free shape parameter (d) representing the dimensionality.</p>

<p>I was interested in fitting parameters to such a distribution, using some distance data from a clustering algorithm.  <a href="https://www.scipy.org/">SciPy</a> comes with a predefined method for fitting generalized gamma parameters, however I wished to implement something similar using <a href="http://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-math/">Apache Commons Math</a>, which does not have native support for fitting a generalized gamma PDF.  I even went so far as to start working out <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2016/06/15/computing-derivatives-of-the-gamma-function/">some of the math</a> needed to augment the Commons Math <a href="http://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-math/apidocs/org/apache/commons/math3/analysis/differentiation/package-summary.html">Automatic Differentiation libraries</a> with Gamma function differentiation needed to numerically fit my parameters.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, I have been fitting a <em>non generalized</em> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_distribution">gamma distribution</a> to the distance data, as a sort of rough cut, using a fast <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_distribution#Maximum_likelihood_estimation">non-iterative approximation</a> to the parameter optimization.  Consistent with my habit of asking the obvious question last, I tried plotting this gamma approximation against distance data, to see how well it compared against the PDF that I derived.</p>

<p>Surprisingly (at least to me), my approximation using the gamma distribution is a very effective fit for spatial dimensionalities <nobr> >= 2 </nobr>:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gamma_approx/approx_plot.png" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p>As the plot shows, only for the 1-dimension case is the gamma approximation substiantially deviating.  In fact, the fit appears to get better as dimensionality increases.  To address the 1D case, I can easily test the fit of a half-gaussian as a possible model.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computing Derivatives of the Gamma Function]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/06/15/computing-derivatives-of-the-gamma-function/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-15T16:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/06/15/computing-derivatives-of-the-gamma-function</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I'll describe a simple algorithm to compute the kth derivatives of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_function">Gamma function</a>.</p>

<p>I'll start by showing a simple recursion relation for these derivatives, and then gives its derivation.  The kth derivative of Gamma(x) can be computed as follows:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/hvqtl52.png" alt="Equation 1" /></p>

<p>The recursive formula for the D<sub>k</sub> functions has an easy inductive proof:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/h79ued9.png" alt="Equation 2" /></p>

<p>Computing the next value D<sub>k</sub> requires knowledge of D<sub>k-1</sub> but also derivative D'<sub>k-1</sub>.  If we start expanding terms, we see the following:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/hhvonpa.png" alt="Equation 3" /></p>

<p>Continuing the process above it is not hard to see that we can continue expanding until we are left only with terms of <nobr>D<sub>1</sub><sup>(*)</sup>(x);</nobr> that is, various derivatives of <nobr>D<sub>1</sub>(x)</nobr>.  Furthermore, each layer of substitutions adds an order to the derivatives, so that we will eventually be left with terms involving the derivatives of <nobr>D<sub>1</sub>(x)</nobr> up to the (k-1)th derivative. Note that these will all be successive orders of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygamma_function">polygamma function</a>.</p>

<p>What we want, to do these computations systematically, is a formula for computing the nth derivative of a term <nobr>D<sub>k</sub>(x)</nobr>.  Examining the first few such derivatives suggests a pattern:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/jqwqpzy.png" alt="Equation 4" /></p>

<p>Generalizing from the above, we see that the formula for the nth derivative is:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/jamccnh.png" alt="Equation 5" /></p>

<p>We are now in a position to fill in the triangular table of values, culminating in the value of <nobr>D<sub>k</sub>(x):</nobr></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dgamma/jj9ph5l.png" alt="Equation 6" /></p>

<p>As previously mentioned, the basis row of values <nobr>D<sub>1</sub><sup>(*)</sup>(x)</nobr> are the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygamma_function">polygamma functions</a> where <nobr>D<sub>1</sub><sup>(n)</sup>(x) = polygamma<sup>(n)</sup>(x)</nobr>.  The first two polygammas, order 0 and 1, are simply the digamma and trigamma functions, respectively, and are available with most numeric libraries.  Computing the general polygamma is a project, and blog post, for another time, but the standard polynomial approximation for the digamma function can of course be differentiated...  Happy Computing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the Effects of Dimensionality on a PDF of Distances]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/06/08/exploring-the-effects-of-dimensionality-on-a-pdf-of-distances/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-08T20:56:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/06/08/exploring-the-effects-of-dimensionality-on-a-pdf-of-distances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every so often I'm reminded that the effects of changing dimensionality on objects and processes can be surprisingly counterintuitive.  Recently I ran across a great example of this, while I working on a model for the distribution of distances in spaces of varying dimension.</p>

<p>Suppose that I draw some values from a classic one-dimensional Gaussian, with zero mean and unit variance, but that I am actually interested in their corresponding distances from center.  Knowing that my Gaussian is centered on the origin, I can rephrase that as: the distribution of magnitudes of values drawn from that Gaussian.  I can simulate this process by actually samping Gaussian values and taking their absolute value.  When I do, I get the following result:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dist_dist/figure1.png" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>It's easy to see -- and intuitive -- that the resulting distribution is a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Half-normal_distribution">half-Gaussian</a>, as I confirmed by overlaying the histogrammed samples above with a half-Gaussian PDF (displayed in green).</p>

<p>I wanted to generalize this basic idea into some arbitrary dimensionality, (d), where I draw d-vectors from an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multivariate_normal_distribution">d-dimensional Gaussian</a> (again, centered on the origin with unit variances). When I take the magnitudes of these sampled d-vectors, what will the probability distribution of <em>their</em> magnitudes look like?</p>

<p>My intuitive assumption was that these magnitudes would <em>also</em> follow a half-Gaussian distribution.  After all, every multivariate Gaussian is densest at its mean, just like the univariate case I examined above.  In fact I was so confident in this assumption that I built my initial modeling around it.  Great confusion ensued, when I saw how poorly my models were working on my higher-dimensional data!</p>

<p>Eventually it occurred to me to do the obvious thing and generate some visualizations from higher dimensional data.  For example, here is the correponding plot generated from a bivariate Gaussian (d=2):</p>

<p><a name="figure2"></a>
<img src="/assets/images/dist_dist/figure2.png" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p>Surprise -- the distribution at d=2 is <em>not even close to half-Gaussian!</em>.  My intuitions couldn't have been more misleading!</p>

<p>Where did I go wrong?</p>

<p>I'll start by observing what happens when I take a multi-dimensional PDF of vectors in (d) dimensions and project it down to a one-dimensional PDF of the corresponding vector magnitudes. To keep things simple, I will be assuming a multi-dimensional PDF <nobr>f<sub>r</sub>(<strong>x</strong><sub>d</sub>)</nobr> that is (1) centered on the origin, and (2) is radially symmetric; the pdf value is the same for all points at a given distance from the origin.  For example, any multivariate Gaussian with <strong>0</strong><sub>d</sub> mean and <strong>I</strong><sub>d</sub> for a covariance matrix satisfies these two assumptions.  With this in mind, you can see that the process of projecting from vectors in <strong>R</strong><sub>d</sub> to their distance from <strong>0</strong><sub>d</sub> (their magnitude) is equivalent to summing all densities <nobr>f<sub>r</sub>(<strong>x</strong><sub>d</sub>)</nobr> along the surface of "d-sphere" radius (r) to obtain a pdf f(r) in distance space.  With assumption (2) we can simplify that integration to just <nobr>f(r)=A<sub>d</sub>(r)f'(r)</nobr>, where f'(r) defines the value of <nobr>f<sub>r</sub>(<strong>x</strong>)</nobr> for all <strong>x</strong> with magnitude of (r), and A<sub>d</sub>(r) is the surface area of a d-sphere with radius (r):</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dist_dist/ztrlusa.png" alt="Figure 3" /></p>

<p>The key observation is that this term is a <em>polynomial</em> function of radius (r), with degree (d-1).  When d=1, it is simply a constant multiplier and so we get the half-Gaussian distribution we expect, but when <nobr>d >= 2</nobr>, the term is zero at r=0, and grows with radius.  Hence we see the in the <a href="#figure2">d=2 plot above</a> that the density begins at zero, then grows with radius until the decreasing gaussian density gradually drives it back toward zero again.</p>

<p>The above ideas can be expressed compactly as follows:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dist_dist/jukgy85.png" alt="Figure 4" /></p>

<p>In my experiments, I am using multivariate Gaussians of mean <strong>0</strong><sub>d</sub> and unit covariance matrix <strong>I</strong><sub>d</sub>, and so the form for f(r;d) becomes:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dist_dist/gwwv5a5.png" alt="Figure 4" /></p>

<p>This form is in fact the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generalized_gamma_distribution">generalized gamma distribution</a>, with scale parameter <nobr>a=2<sup>1/2</sup>,</nobr> shape parameter p=2, and free shape parameter (d) representing the dimensionality in this context.</p>

<p>I can verify that this PDF is correct by plotting it against randomly sampled data at differing dimensions:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/dist_dist/figure3.png" alt="Figure 5" /></p>

<p>This plot demonstrates both that the PDF expression is correct for varying dimensionalities and also illustrates how the shape of the PDF evolves as dimensionality changes.  For me, it was a great example of challenging my intuitions and learning something completely unexpected about the interplay of distances and dimension.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
