<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: math | tool monkey]]></title>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/categories/math/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-23T13:01:11-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erik Erlandson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[erikerlandson@yahoo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Computing Simplex Vertex Locations From Pairwise Object Distances]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/03/26/computing-simplex-vertex-locations-from-pairwise-vertex-distances/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-26T16:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2016/03/26/computing-simplex-vertex-locations-from-pairwise-vertex-distances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Suppose I have a collection of (N) objects, and distances d(j,k) between each pair of objects (j) and (k); that is, my objects are members of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metric_space">metric space</a>.  I have no knowledge about my objects, beyond these pair-wise distances.  These objects could be construed as vertices in an (N-1) dimensional <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simplex">simplex</a>.  However, since I have no spatial information about my objects, I first need a way to assign spatial locations to each object, in vector space R<sup>(N-1),</sup> with only my object distances to work with.</p>

<p>In this post I will derive an algorithm for assigning vertex locations in R<sup>(N-1)</sup> for each of N objects, using only pairwise object distances.</p>

<p>I will assume that N >= 2, since at least two object are required to define a pairwise distance.  The case N=2 is easy, as I can assign vertex 1 to the origin, and vertex 2 to the point d(1,2), to form a 1-simplex (i.e. a line segment) whose single edge is just the distance between the two objects.  I will also assume that my N objects are distinct; that is, each pair has a non-zero distance.</p>

<p>Next consider an arbitrary N, and suppose I have already added vertices 1 through k.  The next vertex (k+1) must obey the pairwise distance relations, as follows:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/jm56vxq.png" alt="figure 1" /></p>

<p>Adding the new vertex (k+1) involves adding another dimension (k) to the simplex.  I define this new kth coordinate x(k) to be zero for the existing k vertices, as annotated above; only the new vertex (k+1) will have a non-zero kth coordinate.  Expanding the quadratic terms on the left yields the following form:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/jtm7dpq.png" alt="figure 2" /></p>

<p>The squared terms for the coordinates of the new vertex (k+1) are inconvenient, however I can get rid of them by subtracting pairs of equations above.  For example, if I subtract equation 1 from the remaining k-1 equations (2 through k), these squared terms disappear, leaving me with the following system of k-1 equations, which we can see is linear in the 1st k-1 coordinates of the new vertex.  Therefore, I know I'll be able to solve for those coordinates.  I can solve for the remaining kth coordinate by plugging it into the first distance equation:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/haovm32.png" alt="figure 3" /></p>

<p>To clarify matters, the equations above can be re-written as the following matrix equation, solveable by any linear systems library:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/h6qdtms.png" alt="figure 4" /></p>

<p>This gives me a recusion relation for adding a new vertex (k+1), given that I have already added the first k vertices.  The basis case of adding the first two vertices was already described above.  And so I can iteratively add all my vertices one at a time by applying the recursion relation.</p>

<p>As a corollary, assume that I have constructed a simplex having k vertices, as shown above, and I would like to assign a spatial location to a new object, (y), given its k distances to each vertex.  The corresponding distance relations are given by:</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/zdw9uv8.png" alt="figure 5" /></p>

<p>I can apply a derivation very similar to the one above, to obtain the following linear equation for the (k-1) coordinates of (y):</p>

<p><img src="http://mathurl.com/zvr5jre.png" alt="figure 6" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Very Fast Reservoir Sampling]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/11/20/very-fast-reservoir-sampling/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-20T11:27:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/11/20/very-fast-reservoir-sampling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I will demonstrate how to do reservoir sampling orders of magnitude faster than the traditional "naive" reservoir sampling algorithm, using a fast high-fidelity approximation to the reservoir sampling-gap distribution.</p>

<blockquote><p>The code I used to collect the data for this post can be viewed <a href="https://github.com/erikerlandson/silex/blob/blog/reservoir/src/main/scala/com/redhat/et/silex/sample/reservoir/reservoir.scala">here</a>.  I generated the plots using the <a href="https://github.com/quantifind/wisp">quantifind WISP</a> project.</p>

<p>Update (April 4, 2016): my colleague <a href="http://rnowling.github.io/">RJ Nowling</a> ran across a <a href="http://www.ittc.ku.edu/~jsv/Papers/Vit87.RandomSampling.pdf">paper by J.S. Vitter</a> that shows Vitter developed the trick of accelerating sampling with a sampling-gap distribution in 1987 -- I re-invented Vitter's wheel 30 years after the fact!  I'm surprised it never caught on, as it is not much harder to implement than the naive version.</p></blockquote>

<p>In a <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/faster-random-samples-with-gap-sampling/">previous post</a>, I showed that random Bernoulli and Poisson sampling could be made much faster by modeling the <em>sampling gap distribution</em> for the corresponding sampling distributions.  More recently, I also began exploring whether <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reservoir_sampling">reservoir sampling</a> might also be optimized using the gap sampling technique, by deriving the <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2015/08/17/the-reservoir-sampling-gap-distribution/">reservoir sampling gap distribution</a>.  For a sampling reservoir of size (R), starting at data element (j), the probability distribution of the sampling gap is:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure6.png" title="Figure 1" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>Modeling a sampling gap distribution is a powerful tool for optimizing a sampling algorithm, but it presupposes that you can actually draw values from that distribution substantially faster than just applying a random process to drawing each data element.  I was unable to come up with a "direct" algorithm for drawing samples from P(k) above (I suspect none exists), however I also know the CDF F(k), so it <em>is</em> possible to apply <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverse_transform_sampling">inversion sampling</a>, which runs in logarithmic time w.r.t the desired accuracy.  Although its logarithmic cost effectively guarantees that it will be a net efficiency win for sufficiently large (j), it still involves a substantial number of computations to yield its samples, and it seems unlikely to be competitive with straight "naive" reservoir sampling over many real-world data sizes, where (j) may never grow very large.</p>

<p>Well, if exact computations are too expensive, we can always look for a fast approximation.  Consider the original "first principles" formula for the sampling gap P(k):</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/figure2.png" title="Figure 2" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p>As the figure above alludes to, if (j) is relatively large compared to (k), then values (j+1),(j+2)...(j+k) are all going to be effectively "close" to (j), and so we can replace them all with (j) as an approximation.  Note that the resulting approximation is just the PMF of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geometric_distribution">geometric distribution</a>, with probability of success p=(R/j), and we already saw how to efficiently draw values from a geometric distribution from our experience with Bernoulli sampling.</p>

<p>Do we have any reason to hope that this approximation will be useful?  For reasons that are similar to those for Bernoulli gap sampling, it will only be efficient to employ gap sampling when the probability (R/j) becomes small enough.  From our experiences with Bernoulli sampling that is <em>at least</em> j>=2R.  So, we have some assurance that (j) itself will be never be <em>very</em> small.  What about (k)?  Note that a geometric distribution "favors" smaller values of (k) -- that is, small values of (k) have the highest probabilities.  In fact, the smaller that (j) is, the larger the probability (R/j) is, and so the more likely that (k) values that are small relative to (j) will be the frequent ones.  It is also promising that the true distribution for P(k) <em>also</em> favors smaller values of (k) (in fact it favors them even a bit more strongly than the approximation).</p>

<p>Although it is encouraging, it is also clear that my argument above is limited to heuristic hand-waving.  What does this approximation really <em>look</em> like, compared to the true distribution?  Fortunately, it is easy to plot both distributions numerically, since we now know the formulas for both:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/CDFs_R=10.png" title="Figure 3" alt="Figure 3" /></p>

<p>The plot above shows that, in fact, the geometric approximation is a <em>surprisingly good</em> approximation to the true distribution!  Furthermore, the approximation remains good as both (j) and (k) grow larger.</p>

<p>Our numeric eye-balling looks quite promising.  Is there an effective way to <em>measure</em> how good this approximation is?  One useful measure is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kolmogorov%E2%80%93Smirnov_test">Kolmogorov-Smirnov D statistic</a>, which is just the maximum absolute error between two cumulative distributions.  Here is a plot of the D statistic for reservoir size R=10, as (j) varies across several magnitudes:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/R=10.png" title="Figure 4" alt="Figure 4" /></p>

<p>This plot is also good news: we can see that deviation, as measured by D, remains bounded at a small value (less than 0.0262).  As this is for the specific value R=10, we also want to know how things change as reservoir size changes:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/R=all.png" title="Figure 5" alt="Figure 5" /></p>

<p>The news is still good!  As reservoir size grows, the approximation only gets better: the D values get smaller as R increases, and remain asymptotically bounded as (j) increases.</p>

<p>Now we have some numeric assurance that the geometric approximation is a good one, and stays good as reservoir size grows and sampling runs get longer.  However, we should also verify that an actual implementation of the approximation works as expected.</p>

<p>Here is pseudocode for an implementation of reservoir sampling using the fast geometric approximation:</p>

<pre><code>// data is array to sample from
// R is the reservoir size
function reservoirFast(data: Array, R: Int) {
  n = data.length
  // Initialize reservoir with first R elements of data:
  res = data[0 until R]
  // Until this threshold, use traditional sampling.  This value may
  // depend on performance characteristics of random number generation and/or
  // numeric libraries:
  t = 4 * R
  j = 1 + R
  while (j &lt; n  &amp;&amp;  j &lt;= t) {
    k = randomInt(j) // random integer &gt;= 0 and &lt; j
    if (k &lt; R) res[k] = data[j]
    j = j + 1
  }
  // Once gaps become significant, it pays to do gap sampling
  while (j &lt; n) {
    // draw gap size (g) from geometric distribution with probability p = R/j
    p = R / j
    u = randomFloat() // random float &gt; 0 and &lt;= 1
    g = floor(log(u) / log(1-p))
    j = j + g
    if (j &lt; n) {
      k = randomInt(R)
      res[k] = data[j]
    }
    j = j + 1
  }
  // return the reservoir
  return res
}
</code></pre>

<p>Following is a plot that shows two-sample D statistics, comparing the distribution in sample gaps between runs of the exact "naive" reservoir sampling with the fast geometric approximation:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/D_naive_vs_fast.png" title="Figure 6" alt="Figure 6" /></p>

<p>As expected, the measured difference in sampling characteristics between naive and fast approximation are small, confirming the numeric predictions.</p>

<p>Since the point of this exercise was to achieve faster random sampling, it remains to measure what kind of speed improvements the fast approximation provides.  As a point of reference, here is a plot of run times for reservoir sampling over 10<sup>8</sup> integers:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/naive_sample_time_vs_R.png" title="Figure 7" alt="Figure 7" /></p>

<p>As expected, sample time remains constant at around 1.5 seconds, regardless of reservoir size, since the naive algorithm always samples from its RNG per each sample.</p>

<p>Compare this to the corresponding plot for the fast geometric approximation:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/gap_sample_times_vs_R.png" title="Figure 8" alt="Figure 8" /></p>

<p>Firstly, we see that the sampling times are <em>much faster</em>, as originally anticipated in my <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2015/08/17/the-reservoir-sampling-gap-distribution/">previous post</a> -- in the neighborhood of 3 orders of magnitude faster.  Secondly, we see that the sampling times do increase as a linear function of reservoir size.  Based on our experience with Bernoulli gap sampling, this is expected; the sampling probabilities are given by (R/j), and therefore the amount of sampling is proportional to R.</p>

<p>Another property anticipated in my previous post was that the efficiency of gap sampling should continue to increase as the amount of data sampled grows; the sampling probability being (R/j), the probability of sampling decreases as j gets larger, and so the corresponding gap sizes grow.  The following plot verifies this property, holding reservoir size R constant, and increasing the data size:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir2/gap_sampling_efficiency.png" title="Figure 9" alt="Figure 9" /></p>

<p>The sampling time (per million elements) decreases as the sample size grows, as predicted by the formula.</p>

<p>In conclusion, I have demonstrated that a geometric distribution can be used as a high quality approximation to the true sampling gap distribution for reservoir sampling, which allows reservoir sampling to be performed much faster than the naive algorithm while still retaining sampling quality.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Reservoir Sampling Gap Distribution]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/08/17/the-reservoir-sampling-gap-distribution/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-17T07:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/08/17/the-reservoir-sampling-gap-distribution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="http://erikerlandson.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/faster-random-samples-with-gap-sampling/">previous post</a>, I showed that random Bernoulli and Poisson sampling could be made much faster by modeling the <em>sampling gap distribution</em> - that is, directly drawing random samples from the distribution of how many elements would be skipped over between actual samples taken.</p>

<p>Another popular sampling algorithm is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reservoir_sampling">Reservoir Sampling</a>.  Its sampling logic is a bit more complicated than Bernoulli or Poisson sampling, in the sense that the probability of sampling any given (jth) element <em>changes</em>. For a sampling reservoir of size R, and all j>R, the probability of choosing element (j) is R/j.  You can see that the potential payoff for gap-sampling is big, particularly as data size becomes large; as (j) approaches infinity, the probability R/j goes to zero, and the corresponding gaps between samples grow without bound.</p>

<p>Modeling a sampling gap distribution is a powerful tool for optimizing a sampling algorithm, but it requires that (1) you actually <em>know</em> the sampling distribution, and (2) that you can effectively draw values from that distribution faster than just applying a random process to drawing each data element.</p>

<p>With that goal in mind, I derived the probability mass function (pmf) and cumulative distribution function (cdf) for the sampling gap distribution of reservoir sampling.  In this post I will show the derivations.</p>

<h3>The Sampling Gap Distribution</h3>

<p>In the interest of making it easy to get at the actual answers, here are the pmf and cdf for the Reservoir Sampling Gap Distribution.  For a sampling reservoir of size (R), starting at data element (j), the probability distribution of the sampling gap is:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure6.png" title="Figure 6" alt="Figure 6" /></p>

<h3>Conventions</h3>

<p>In the derivations that follow, I will keep to some conventions:</p>

<ul>
<li>R = the sampling reservoir size.  R > 0.</li>
<li>j = the index of a data element being considered for sampling.  j > R.</li>
<li>k = the size of a gap between samples.  k >= 0.</li>
</ul>


<p>P(k) is the probability that the gap between one sample and the next is of size k.  The support for P(k) is over all k>=0.  I will generally assume that j>R, as the first R samples are always loaded into the reservoir and the actual random sampling logic starts at j=R+1.  The constraint j>R will also be relevant to many binomial coefficient expressions, where it ensures the coefficient is well defined.</p>

<h3>Deriving the Probability Mass Function, P(k)</h3>

<p>Suppose we just chose (randomly) to sample data element (j-1).  Now we are interested in the probability distribution of the next sampling gap.  That is, the probability P(k) that we will <em>not</em> sample the next (k) elements {j,j+1,...j+k-1}, and sample element (j+k):</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure1.png" title="Figure 1" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>By arranging the product terms in descending order as above, you can see that they can be written as factorial quotients:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure2.png" title="Figure 2" alt="Figure 2" /></p>

<p>Now we apply <a href="#LemmaA">Lemma A</a>.  The 2nd case (a&lt;=b) of the Lemma applies, since (j-1-R)&lt;=j, so we have:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure3.png" title="Figure 3" alt="Figure 3" /></p>

<p>And so we have now derived a compact, closed-form expression for P(k).</p>

<h3>Deriving the Cumulative Distribution Function, F(k)</h3>

<p>Now that we have a derivation for the pmf P(k), we can tackle a derivation for the cdf.  First I will make note of this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_coefficient#Series_involving_binomial_coefficients">useful identity</a> that I scraped off of Wikipedia (I substituted (x) => (a) and (k) => (b)):</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/identity1.png" title="identity 1" alt="identity 1" /></p>

<p>The cumulative distribution function for the sampling gap, F(k), is of course just the sum over P(t), for (t) from 0 up to (k):</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure4.png" title="Figure 4" alt="Figure 4" /></p>

<p>This is a closed-form solution, but we can apply a bit more simplification:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure5.png" title="Figure 5" alt="Figure 5" /></p>

<h3>Conclusions</h3>

<p>We have derived closed-form expressions for the pmf and cdf of the Reservoir Sampling gap distribution:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/figure6.png" title="Figure 6" alt="Figure 6" /></p>

<p>In order to apply these results to a practical gap-sampling implementation of Reservoir Sampling, we would next need a way to efficiently sample from P(k), to obtain gap sizes to skip over.  How to accomplish this is an open question, but knowing a formula for P(k) and F(k) is a start.</p>

<h3>Acknowledgements</h3>

<p>Many thanks to <a href="http://rnowling.github.io/">RJ Nowling</a> and <a href="http://chapeau.freevariable.com/">Will Benton</a> for proof reading and moral support!  Any remaining errors are my own fault.</p>

<p><a name="LemmaA"></a></p>

<h3>Lemma A, And Its Proof</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/lemmaA.png" title="Lemma A" alt="Lemma A" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/reservoir1/lemmaAproof.png" title="Lemma A Proof" alt="Lemma A Proof" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Generalizing Kendall's Tau]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/08/14/generalizing-kendalls-tau/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-14T14:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2015/08/14/generalizing-kendalls-tau</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I have been applying <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kendall_rank_correlation_coefficient">Kendall's Tau</a> as an evaluation metric to assess how well a regression model ranks input samples, with respect to a known correct ranking.</p>

<p>The process of implementing the Kendall's Tau statistic, with my software engineer's hat on, caused me to reflect a bit on how it could be generalized beyond the traditional application of ranking numeric pairs.  In this post I'll discuss the generalization of Kendall's Tau to non-numeric data, and also generalizing from totally ordered data to partial orderings.</p>

<h5>A Review of Kendall's Tau</h5>

<p>I'll start with a brief review of Kendall's Tau.  For more depth, a good place to start is the Wikipedia article at the link above.</p>

<p>Consider a sequence of (n) observations where each observation is a pair (x,y), where we wish to measure how well a ranking by x-values agrees with a ranking by the y-values.  Informally, Kendall's Tau (aka the Kendall Rank Correlation Coefficient) is the difference between number of observation-pairs (pairs of pairs, if you will) whose ordering <em>agrees</em> ("concordant" pairs) and the number of such pairs whose ordering <em>disagrees</em> ("discordant" pairs).  This difference is divided by the total number of observation pairs.</p>

<p>The commonly-used formulation of Kendall's Tau is the "Tau-B" statistic, which accounts for observed pairs having tied values in either x or y as being neither concordant nor discordant:</p>

<h6>Figure 1: Kendall's Tau-B</h6>

<p><img src="/assets/images/kendalls_tau/figure_1.png" title="Kendall's Tau" alt="Kendall's Tau" /></p>

<p>The formulation above has quadratic complexity, with respect to data size (n).  It is possible to rearrange this computation in a way that can be computed in (n)log(n) time[1]:</p>

<h6>Figure 2: An (n)log(n) formulation of Kendall's Tau-B</h6>

<p><img src="/assets/images/kendalls_tau/figure_2.png" title="Kendall's Tau" alt="Kendall's Tau" /></p>

<p>The details of performing this computation can be found at [1] or on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kendall_rank_correlation_coefficient#Algorithms">Wikipedia entry</a>.  For my purposes, I'll note that it requires two (n)log(n) sorts of the data, which becomes relevant below.</p>

<h5>Generalizing to Non-Numeric Values</h5>

<p>Generalizing Kendall's Tau to non-numeric values is mostly just making the observation that the definition of "concordant" and "discordant" pairs is purely based on comparing x-values and y-values (and, in the (n)log(n) formulation, performing sorts on the data).  From the software engineer's perspective this means that the computations are well defined on any data type with an ordering relation, which includes numeric types but also chars, strings, sequences of any element supporting an ordering, etc.  Significantly, most programming languages support the concept of defining ordering relations on arbitrary data types, which means that <em><em>Kendall's Tau can, in principle, be computed on literally any kind of data structure</em></em>, provided you supply it with a well defined ordering.  Furthermore, an examination of the algorithms shows that values of x and y need not even be of the same type, nor do they require the same ordering.</p>

<h5>Generalizing to Partial Orderings</h5>

<p>When I brought this observation up, my colleague <a href="http://chapeau.freevariable.com/">Will Benton</a> asked the very interesting question of whether it's also possible to compute Kendall's Tau on objects that have only a <em>partial ordering</em>.  It turns out that you <em><em>can</em></em> define Kendall's Tau on partially ordered data, by defining the case of two non-comparable x-values, or y-values, as another kind of tie.</p>

<p>The big caveat with this definition is that the (n)log(n) optimization does not apply.  Firstly, the optimized algorithm relies heavily on (n)log(n) sorting, and there is no unique full sorting of elements that are only partially ordered.  Secondly, the formula's definition of the quantities n1, n2 and n3 is founded on the assumption that element equality is transitive; this is why you can count a number of tied values, t, and use t(t-1)/2 as the corresponding number of tied pairs.  But in a partial ordering, this assumption is violated. Consider the case where (a) &lt; (b), but (a) is non-comparable to (c) and (b) is also non-comparable to (c).  By our definition, (a) is tied with (c), and (c) is tied with (b), but transitivity is violated, as (a) &lt; (b).</p>

<p>So how <em>can</em> we compute Tau in this case?  Consider (n1) and (n2), in Figure-1.  These values represent the number of pairs that were tied wrt (x) and (y), respectively.  We can't use the shortcut formulas for (n1) and (n2), but we can count them directly, pair by pair, simply by conducting the traditional quadratic iteration over pairs, and incrementing (n1) whenever two x-values are noncomparable, and incrementing (n2) whenever two y-values are non-comparable, just as we increment (nc) and (nd) to count concordant and discordant pairs.  With this modification, we can apply the formula in Figure-1 as-is.</p>

<h5>Conclusions</h5>

<p>I made these observations without any particular application in mind. However, my instincts as a software engineer tell me that making generalizations in this way often paves the way for new ideas, once the generalized concept is made available.  With luck, it will inspire either me or somebody else to apply Kendall's Tau in interesting new ways.</p>

<h5>References</h5>

<p>[1] Knight, W. (1966). "A Computer Method for Calculating Kendall's Tau with Ungrouped Data". Journal of the American Statistical Association 61 (314): 436–439. doi:10.2307/2282833. JSTOR 2282833.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smooth Gradients for Cubic Hermite Splines]]></title>
    <link href="http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/03/16/smooth-gradients-for-cubic-hermite-splines/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-16T07:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://erikerlandson.github.com/blog/2013/03/16/smooth-gradients-for-cubic-hermite-splines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the advantages of cubic Hermite splines is that their interval interpolation formula is an explicit function of gradients \( m_0, m_1, ... m_{n-1} \) at knot-points:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
y(t) = h_{00}(t) y_j + h_{10}(t) m_j + h_{01}(t) y_{j+1} + h_{11}(t) m_{j+1} \\\\
\\]
</div>


<p>where the Hermite bases are:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
h_{00} = 2t^3 - 3t^2 + 1 \\\\
h_{10} = t^3 - 2t^2 + t \\\\
h_{01} = -2t^3 + 3t^2 \\\\
h_{11} = t^3 - t^2 \\\\
\\]
</div>


<p>(For now, I will be using the unit-interval form of the interpolation, where t runs from 0 to 1 on each interval.  I will also discuss the non-uniform interval equations below)</p>

<p>This formulation allows one to explicitly specify the interpolation gradient at each knot point, and to choose from various gradient assignment policies, for example <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cubic_Hermite_spline#Interpolating_a_data_set">those listed here</a>, even supporting policies for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monotone_cubic_interpolation">enforcing monotonic interpolations</a>.</p>

<p>One important caveat with cubic Hermite splines is that although the gradient \( y'(t) \) is guaranteed to be continuous, it is <em>not</em> guaranteed to be smooth (that is, differentiable) <em>across</em> the knots (it is of course smooth <em>inside</em> each interval). Therefore, another useful category of gradient policy is to obtain gradients \( m_0, m_1, ... m_{n-1} \) such that \( y'(t) \) is also smooth across knots.</p>

<p>(I feel sure that what follows was long since derived elsewhere, but my attempts to dig the formulation up on the internet failed, and so I decided the derivation might make a useful blog post)</p>

<p>To ensure smooth gradient across knot points, we want the 2nd derivative \( y"(t) \) to be equal at the boundaries of adjacent intervals:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
h_{00}^"(t) y_{j-1} + h_{10}^"(t) m_{j-1} + h_{01}^"(t) y_j + h_{11}^"(t) m_j \\\\
= \\\\
h_{00}^"(t) y_j + h_{10}^"(t) m_j + h_{01}^"(t) y_{j+1} + h_{11}^"(t) m_{j+1}
\\]
</div>


<p>or substituting the 2nd derivative of the basis definitions above:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
\\left( 12 t - 6 \\right) y_{j-1} + \\left( 6 t - 4 \\right) m_{j-1}  + \\left( 6 - 12 t \\right) y_j + \\left( 6 t - 2 \\right) m_j \\\\
= \\\\
\\left( 12 t - 6 \\right) y_{j} + \\left( 6 t - 4 \\right) m_{j}  + \\left( 6 - 12 t \\right) y_{j+1} + \\left( 6 t - 2 \\right) m_{j+1}
\\]
</div>


<p>Observe that t = 1 on the left hand side of this equation, and t = 0 on the right side, and so we have:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
6 y_{j-1} + 2 m_{j-1} - 6 y_j + 4 m_j
=
-6 y_j - 4 m_j + 6 y_{j+1} - 2 m_{j+1}
\\]
</div>


<p>which we can rearrange as:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
2 m_{j-1} + 8 m_j + 2 m_{j+1}
=
6 \\left( y_{j+1} - y_{j-1} \\right)
\\]
</div>


<p>Given n knot points, the above equation holds for j = 1 to n-2 (using zero-based indexing, as nature intended).  Once we define equations for j = 0 and j = n-1, we will have a system of equations to solve.  There are two likely choices.  The first is to simply specify the endpoint gradients \( m_0 = G \) and \( m_{n-1} = H \) directly, which yields the following <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tridiagonal_matrix_algorithm">tri-diagonal matrix equation:</a></p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
\\left( \\begin{array} {ccccc}
1 &   &   &   &   \\\\
2 & 8 & 2 &   &   \\\\
  & 2 & 8 & 2 &   \\\\
  &   & \\vdots &   &   \\\\
  &   & 2 & 8 & 2 \\\\ 
  &   &   &   & 1 \\\\
\\end{array} \\right)

\\left( \\begin{array} {c}
m_0 \\\\
m_1 \\\\
 \\\\
\\vdots \\\\
 \\\\
m_{n-1}
\\end{array} \\right)
=
\\left( \\begin{array} {c}
G \\\\
6 \\left( y_2 - y_0 \\right) \\\\
6 \\left( y_3 - y_1 \\right) \\\\
\\vdots \\\\
6 \\left( y_{n-1} - y_{n-3} \\right) \\\\
H \\\\
\\end{array} \\right)
\\]
</div>


<p>The second common endpoint policy is to set the 2nd derivative equal to zero -- the "natural spline."   Setting the 2nd derivative to zero at the left-end knot (and t = 0) gives us:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
4 m_0 + 2 m_1   =   6 \\left( y_1 - y_0 \\right)
\\]
</div>


<p>Similarly, at the right-end knot (t = 1), we have:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
2 m_0 + 4 m_1   =   6 \\left( y_{n-1} - y_{n-2} \\right)
\\]
</div>


<p>And so for a natural spline endpoint policy the matrix equation looks like this:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
\\left( \\begin{array} {ccccc}
4 & 2 &   &   &   \\\\
2 & 8 & 2 &   &   \\\\
  & 2 & 8 & 2 &   \\\\
  &   & \\vdots &   &   \\\\
  &   & 2 & 8 & 2 \\\\ 
  &   &   & 2 & 4 \\\\
\\end{array} \\right)

\\left( \\begin{array} {c}
m_0 \\\\
m_1 \\\\
 \\\\
\\vdots \\\\
 \\\\
m_{n-1}
\\end{array} \\right)
=
\\left( \\begin{array} {c}
6 \\left( y_1 - y_0 \\right) \\\\
6 \\left( y_2 - y_0 \\right) \\\\
6 \\left( y_3 - y_1 \\right) \\\\
\\vdots \\\\
6 \\left( y_{n-1} - y_{n-3} \\right) \\\\
6 \\left( y_{n-1} - y_{n-2} \\right) \\\\
\\end{array} \\right)
\\]
</div>


<p>The derivation above is for uniform (and unit) intervals, where t runs from 0 to 1 on each knot interval.  I'll now discuss the variation where knot intervals are non-uniform.   The non-uniform form of the interpolation equation is:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
y(x) = h_{00}(t) y_j + h_{10}(t) d_j m_j + h_{01}(t) y_{j+1} + h_{11}(t) d_j m_{j+1} \\\\
\\text{ } \\\\
\\text{where:} \\\\
\\text{ }  \\\\
d_j = x_{j+1} - x_j \\text{  for  } j = 0, 1, ... n-2 \\\\
t = (x - x_j) / d_j
\\]
</div>


<p>Taking \( t = t(x) \) and applying the chain rule, we see that 2nd derivative equation now looks like:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
y"(x) = \\frac { \\left( 12 t - 6 \\right) y_{j} + \\left( 6 t - 4 \\right) d_j m_{j}  + \\left( 6 - 12 t \\right) y_{j+1} + \\left( 6 t - 2 \\right) d_j m_{j+1} } { d_j^2 }
\\]
</div>


<p>Applying a derivation similar to the above, we find that our (interior) equations look like this:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
\\frac {2} { d_{j-1} }  m_{j-1} + \\left( \\frac {4} { d_{j-1} } + \\frac {4} { d_j } \\right) m_j + \\frac {2} {d_j} m_{j+1}
=
\\frac { 6 \\left( y_{j+1} - y_{j} \\right) } { d_j^2 } + \\frac { 6 \\left( y_{j} - y_{j-1} \\right) } { d_{j-1}^2 }
\\]
</div>


<p>and natural spline endpoint equations are:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
\\text{left:  } \\frac {4} {d_0} m_0 + \\frac {2} {d_0} m_1   =   \\frac {6 \\left( y_1 - y_0 \\right)} {d_0^2} \\\\
\\text{right: } \\frac {2} {d_{n-2}} m_0 + \\frac {4} {d_{n-2}} m_1   =   \\frac {6 \\left( y_{n-1} - y_{n-2} \\right)} {d_{n-2}^2}
\\]
</div>


<p>And so the matrix equation for specified endpoint gradients is:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
\\scriptsize
\\left( \\begin{array} {ccccc}
\\normalsize 1 \\scriptsize &   &   &   &   \\\\
\\frac{2}{d_0} & \\frac{4}{d_0} {+} \\frac{4}{d_1} & \\frac{2}{d_1} &   &   \\\\
  & \\frac{2}{d_1} & \\frac{4}{d_1} {+} \\frac{4}{d_2} & \\frac{2}{d_2} &   \\\\
  &   & \\vdots &   &   \\\\
  &   & \\frac{2}{d_{n-3}} & \\frac{4}{d_{n-3}} {+} \\frac{4}{d_{n-2}} & \\frac{2}{d_{n-2}} \\\\ 
  &   &   &   & \\normalsize 1 \\scriptsize \\\\
\\end{array} \\right)

\\left( \\begin{array} {c}
m_0 \\\\
m_1 \\\\
 \\\\
\\vdots \\\\
 \\\\
m_{n-1}
\\end{array} \\right)
=
\\left( \\begin{array} {c}
G \\\\
6 \\left( \\frac{y_2 {-} y_1}{d_1^2} {+} \\frac{y_1 {-} y_0}{d_0^2} \\right) \\\\
6 \\left( \\frac{y_3 {-} y_2}{d_2^2} {+} \\frac{y_2 {-} y_1}{d_1^2} \\right)  \\\\
\\vdots \\\\
6 \\left( \\frac{y_{n-1} {-} y_{n-2}}{d_{n-2}^2} {+} \\frac{y_{n-2} {-} y_{n-3}}{d_{n-3}^2} \\right) \\\\
H \\\\
\\end{array} \\right)
\\normalsize
\\]
</div>


<p>And the equation for natural spline endpoints is:</p>

<div markdown="0">
\\[
\\scriptsize
\\left( \\begin{array} {ccccc}
\\frac{4}{d_0} & \\frac{2}{d_0}  &   &   &   \\\\
\\frac {2} {d_0} & \\frac {4} {d_0} {+} \\frac {4} {d_1} & \\frac{2}{d_1} &   &   \\\\
  & \\frac{2}{d_1} & \\frac{4}{d_1} {+} \\frac{4}{d_2} & \\frac{2}{d_2} &   \\\\
  &   & \\vdots &   &   \\\\
  &   & \\frac{2}{d_{n-3}} & \\frac{4}{d_{n-3}} {+} \\frac{4}{d_{n-2}} & \\frac{2}{d_{n-2}} \\\\ 
  &   &   & \\frac{2}{d_{n-2}} & \\frac{4}{d_{n-2}} \\\\
\\end{array} \\right)

\\left( \\begin{array} {c}
m_0 \\\\
m_1 \\\\
 \\\\
\\vdots \\\\
 \\\\
m_{n-1}
\\end{array} \\right)
=
\\left( \\begin{array} {c}
\\frac{6 \\left( y_1 {-} y_0 \\right)}{d_0^2} \\\\
6 \\left( \\frac{y_2 {-} y_1}{d_1^2}  {+}  \\frac{y_1 {-} y_0}{d_0^2} \\right) \\\\
6 \\left( \\frac{y_3 {-} y_2}{d_2^2}  {+}  \\frac{y_2 {-} y_1}{d_1^2} \\right)  \\\\
\\vdots \\\\
6 \\left( \\frac{y_{n-1} {-} y_{n-2}}{d_{n-2}^2}  {+}  \\frac{y_{n-2} {-} y_{n-3}}{d_{n-3}^2} \\right) \\\\
\\frac{6 \\left( y_{n-1} {-} y_{n-2} \\right)}{d_{n-2}^2} \\\\
\\end{array} \\right)
\\normalsize
\\]
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
